<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God's goodness to this Israel in all ages being the substance of some sermons on Psalm LXXIII, I/ by J.F., minister of the gospel.</title>
            <author>J. F. (James Forbs), 1629?-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39885</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32028</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12295654</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12295654</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59023</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39885)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59023)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1503:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God's goodness to this Israel in all ages being the substance of some sermons on Psalm LXXIII, I/ by J.F., minister of the gospel.</title>
                  <author>J. F. (James Forbs), 1629?-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 91 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Truly God is good to Israel, even to such as are of a clean heart."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect : pages torn. Title page-page 11 from Harvard copy spliced at end.</note>
                  <note>Errata : p. [2] on Harvard copy spliced at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXIII, 1 --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59023:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>God's Goodneſs TO HIS ISRAEL In All Ages.</p>
            <p>Being the Subſtance of ſome SERMONS, ON PSALM Lxxiii. 1.</p>
            <q>Truly God is good to Iſrael, even to ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are of a clean heart.</q>
            <p>By <hi>J. F.</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:59023:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59023:2"/>
            <head>God's Goodneſs TO HIS ISRAEL <hi>In all Ages.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm LXXIII. 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Truly God is good to Iſrael, and to ſuch as are of a clean heart.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THEY that will be at pains to peruſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pſalm throughout, will eaſily perce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> under what a ſad tepmtation the Pſalm (whether <hi>Aſaph</hi> or <hi>David,</hi> is not mater<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> had been at this time, having obſerved how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wicked proſpered, and what miſeries the godly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> undergo; he did begin to conclude that it wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> great matter whether he followed the ways of g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lineſs any more; or whether he turned Profane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Atheiſtical: v. 2, 3. <hi>As for me my feet were alm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> gone, my ſteps had well nigh ſlipt; for I was envio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> at the fooliſh, when I ſaw the proſperity of the wicked</hi> v. 13, 14. <hi>Verily I have cleanſed my heart in vain and waſhed my hands in innocency; for all the day long
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59023:3"/>have I been plagued, and chaſtened every morning.</hi> While thus he was conflicting with the temptation, the Lord directed him to the uſe of a bleſſed means, whereby he came to be better inſtructed; <hi>He went into the ſanctuary (i.e.</hi> he conſulted the Oracles of God, he ſearched the Records of Heaven, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, he was diligent in the practice of all duties of Temple-worſhip, then in uſe; he conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with God and his Spirit, and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Sactuary was the Type and he the Antitype) and then he could ſay, <hi>Surely thou haſt ſet them in ſlippery places; thou caſteſt them down into deſtruction: how are they brought into deſolation, as in a moment? they are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly conſumed with terrours, as a dream, when one awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; ſo, O Lord, when thou awakeſt, ſhalt thou deſpiſe their image.</hi> Having now overcome the temptation, he pens this Pſalm, an excellent Proſpective Glaſs for the Church and People of God in all ages; wherein they may ſee, 1. The variety and wonderfulneſs of the Diſpenſations of Gods Providence towards his Creatures. 2. That its common and ordinary, for wicked men, to have worldly proſperity. 3. That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tentimes, as to outward things, Saints <hi>are of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>men the moſt miſerable;</hi> ſo 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. to the end, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 22. <hi>We are accounted all day long as ſheep for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ughter.</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That they that are moſt ſpiritual, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ble to temptations, and in a readineſs to comply <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>erewith, and therefore let him who thinks he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nds, take heed leſt he fall. 5. One of the beſt means under heaven to get victory over a temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, is to go into the Sanctuary, taking it in the fore-mentioned ſenſe. Laſtly, Tempted ones ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this courſe to wait upon God, in the uſe of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed means, have ſometime or other a glorious iſſue; and not only ſo, but they prove the moſt choice and excellent, the moſt humble and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:59023:3"/>the moſt affectionate and loving, the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt excelling and Soul edifying Chriſtians; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> improve their temptations, their Exerciſes unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, and their iſſues out of them to ſome purpoſe for the glory of God, the good of their own ſouls, and the ſpiritual advantage of others. This im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement the Pſalmiſt made, is worthy of our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. 1. He is now able with a holy aſſevera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to atteſt to this truth which he did ſo unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly queſtion, <hi>Truly God is good to Iſrael.</hi> 2. He bemoans his bruitiſhneſs, ſtupidity, and atheiſtical ignorance, v. 22. <hi>So fooliſh was I and ignorant, I was as a beaſt before thee.</hi> 3. He did attribute his preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation from yielding to temptation, to the divine ſupports of the free grace of God only; v. 23. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs thou art continually with me, thou haſt holden me by thy right hand.</hi> 4. By the mercy received, he is engaged to act a fiducial dependance upon God as long as he lives; v. 24 <hi>Thou ſhalt guid me with thy counſel, and afterward receive me to glory.</hi> 5. He has more ſublimated, raiſed, and elevated affections than ever; v. 25. <hi>Whom have I in heaven but thee, there is none in all the earth I deſire beſides thee.</hi> Laſtly, He is fully grounded, ſettled, and eſtabliſhed in this truth, that let the wicked pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper a thouſand times over, yet wo ſhall be to them in concluſion, v. 27. <hi>For lo they that are from thee, ſhall periſh, thou haſt deſtroyed</hi> (it's as ſure as if thou hadſt already done it) <hi>all them that go a whoring from thee:</hi> and on the contrary, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owns of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence on Gods people, ſhall never make him out of love with holineſs: I ſhall ſtill ſay, <hi>It is good for me to draw near to God; I have put my truſt in the Lord, that I may declare all thy works.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59023:4"/>
            <p>Thus you ſee how the ſcope of the whole Pſalm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oes ſo much conduce to the clearing of what is contained in the firſt verſe, <hi>Truly God is good to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> Some read the firſt word, <hi>Although,</hi> or, <hi>Yet ſurely, i.e.</hi> Though once I was under a ſtrong temptation, the Devil and my own carnal heart, would have perſwaded me that God did not care for his people: Notwithſtanding that to ſenſe and reaſon, providences do often ſpeak forth the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the wicked, and the godlies miſeries; though this be the Opinion of the vulgar and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort of people, yet now I can ſet my ſeal to this truth, <hi>God is good to Iſrael,</hi> with a <hi>ſurely,</hi> a <hi>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> a <hi>verily.</hi> In the words there are theſe two things that need explication; 1. Who are the <hi>Iſrael</hi> here ſpoken of. 2. What we are to underſtand by thoſe that <hi>are of a clean heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, <hi>Iſrael</hi> was that Name which God gave unto <hi>Jacob</hi> after he had wreſtled with the angel and prevailed; <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.28. <hi>Thy name ſhall be called no more Jacob, but Iſrael, for as a Prince haſt thou power with God and with men, and haſt prevailed;</hi> Hoſ. 12.13. The reaſon of the change of Name was no doubt for honours ſake. Sometimes it ſignifies all the poſterity of <hi>Jacob,</hi> Iſa. 48.1. <hi>Hear this O houſe of Jacob, which art called by the name of Iſrael,</hi> Rom. 9.4. 2 Cor. 11.23. Phil. 3.5. Sometimes for the Church under the Old Teſtament, conſiſting of the poſterity of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and Gentile Proſelytes; Pſal. 68.35. <hi>The God of Iſrael is he that giveth ſtrength and power to his people;</hi> and 125. laſt. Joh. 1.49. Rom. 9.6. For the Chriſtian Church under the New Teſtament converted to the faith of Chriſt; <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.18. <hi>He is not a Jew, which is one outwardly; neither is that circumciſion, which is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59023:4"/>in the fleſh: but he is a Jew, which is one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly; and circumciſion is that of the heart, in the ſpirit, and not in the letter; whoſe praiſe is not of men, but of God:</hi> Rom. 2.28, 29. When this Pſalm was firſt penned, by <hi>Iſrael</hi> here ſpoken of, the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament Church were principally underſtood, but in our treating of this Subject, we are not to reſtrict it to them only.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we may the better know who thoſe of <hi>a clean heart</hi> are, this diſtinction is neceſſary: 1. There is a Legal cleanneſs of heart, which is a perfect and compleat purity, according to what the Law requires. 2. There is an Evangelical or Goſpel cleanneſs of heart, which is, 1. A godly ſorrow and humiliation from heart-uncleanneſs. 2. A holy deteſtation, hatred, and abhorrence of every ſin. 3. A conſtant endeavour every day more and more to be rid of ſin. 4. A ſincere cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial love to holineſs and heart purity. 5. A fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and earneſt praying with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 51. <hi>Create in me a clean heart, and renue a right ſpirit within me.</hi> 6. An unfeigned faith, whereby a hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſoul, does notwithſtanding of the guilt and filth of ſin, lay hold on Chriſt for Juſtification and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification. It's of this later and not the former, the aſſertion in the Text is verified; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1, 2. <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe ſins is forgiven, and whoſe tranſgreſſion is covered; bleſſed is the man unto whom the Lord imputeth not iniquity, and in whoſe ſpirit there is no guil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time you may perceive that my Text points at theſe three things: 1. The goodneſs of God here mentioned, it not that common provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential bounty whereof the whole Creation are made partakers, but the ſpecialties of Gods love and favour. 2. Though there are many titular
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59023:5"/>Chriſtians that go under the name of Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, Saints, and Profeſſors, yet the ſpecialty of Love, is the peculiar priviledge and portion of up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right-hearted ones only. 3. It is a moſt infallible, certain, and undoubted truth, that God is good to his Church and people, eſpecially ſuch as are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſouls amongſt them. O how ſweet is it to ſpeak of this goodneſs of God, but how much more ſweet to taſte of it: O its ſweet to know it, but much more ſweet to feel it experimentally, and to have a lively ſenſe of his goodneſs to my own ſoul in particular.</p>
            <p>For the opening of this more fully, I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this method, 1. Give ſome few Scripture-proofs of this truth, God is good to his people. 2. Some demonſtrations thereof, from what has been common to his people in all ages. 3. From ſome particular bleſſings beſtowed upon the Jews under the Old Teſtament. 4. What the goodneſs of God was to the Goſpel-Church, as in contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction to the Jews. 5. What were the peculiar bleſſings of God to the Primitive Church, in Chriſt and the Apoſtles days. 6. Wherein the goodneſs of God appeared to the Church for the firſt Three hundred years after the death of Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. 7. What from the firſt riſe of Antichriſt, till he came to his full height, and during his reign. 8. What the good providence of God is like to be from the firſt remarkable beginning of Antichriſts ruin, to the time and period of his utter deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from the beginning of the work of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the end of the World.</p>
            <p>Here's Work enough carved out for me to ſpeak, and you to hear of; we may well ſay, Who is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for theſe things? We might be greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, even at our firſt entrance upon it, were
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59023:5"/>it not for this one thing, That God with whom we have to do, and whoſe work we are about, is of infinite goodneſs, grace, mercy, love, and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, abundant in goodneſs and truth; <hi>he giveth li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally, and upbraideth no man,</hi> Jam. 1.5.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For Scripture proofs take theſe few inſtead of many, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.19. <hi>O how great is thy goodneſs which thou haſt laid up for them that fear thee; which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou haſt wrought for them that truſt in thee, before the ſons of men!</hi> Zech. 3. laſt ver. Pſal. 103.11, 12, 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15, 16, 17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 107. this is four or five <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imes reiterated, <hi>O that men would praiſe the Lord, for his goodneſs and for his wonderful works to the ſons of men;</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136. this is 26 times repeated, <hi>The mercy of the Lord endureth for ever.</hi> and 145.7, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 9. <hi>They ſhall abundantly utter the memory of thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat goodneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſhall ſing of thy righteouſneſs; the Lord is gracious and full of compaſſion, ſlow to anger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd of great mercy; the Lord is good to all, and his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er mercies are ever all his works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The conſideration of ſuch bleſſings as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re common to the upright hearted ones in all ages, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a farther demonſtration of this truth, and they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re theſe: 1. There's none of them, but it was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the heart of God to do them good before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oundation of the world; <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. 2. That unſpeakable and unparallell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d mercy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God in promiſing and ſending his dear Son to work redemption for his people, is a confirmation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f this. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3 16. <hi>God ſo loved the world</hi> 3. There's one of Gods peculiar ones, but in due time have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een effectually called from darkneſs to light; he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>kes the heirs of hell, wrath, and damnation; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dopts them for his own children; 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old what manner of love and goodneſs this is. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pardon of ſin is that that all the people of God
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59023:6"/>have been partakers of; <hi>Micah</hi> 7.18. O who is a God like unto our God, <hi>that pardoneth iniquity, and paſſeth by the tranſgreſſion of the remnant of his heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage!</hi> Iſa. 43.25. Ezek. 36.22. 5. All ſuch have had the ſoul-ſaving and ſanctifying graces of the ſpirit beſtowed upon them; 2 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.4. 6. They have had Ordinances and means, whereby grace and all ſpiritual bleſſings may be communicated to them; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19, 20. <hi>He ſheweth his word to Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, his ſtatutes and his judgments to Iſrael; he hath not dealt ſo with any Nation</hi> — 7. Whatever bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings they have, all is by the tenure of a Covenant of Grace; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.. <hi>All promiſes are Yea and Amen in Chriſt to them that believe.</hi> O the never-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough-admired goodneſs of this God, that has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcended ſo far, as by a voluntary Contract and Covenant to make himſelf a Debtor to ſuch unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving wretches! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.3. O <hi>come let us magnifie the goodneſs of the Lord together!</hi> 8. God is ſo good, that he has in all ages furniſhed his people with what he knew to be moſt convenient for them; if the light of his countenance was beſt for them, than they had; if the joys and conſolations of the Holy Ghoſt, if the hidings of his face — if poverties, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aches, if Ordinances, or if ſometimes the want of Ordinances, was good for them; if perſecution, or deliverance from it — He has ſanctified every ſtate and condition, making all things work for their good; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. in one word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. <hi>The Lord is a Sun and a Shield, he giveth grace and glory, no good thing will he with-hold from them that walk uprightly:</hi> and 37.37. <hi>Mark the perfect man and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the upright, behold the end of that man is peace Iſa.</hi> 64.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.12. <hi>Many, O Lord my God, are thy wonderful works, which thou haſt done, and thy thoughts which are to us-ward; they cannot be reckoned up
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59023:6"/>in order before thee, if I would declare and ſpeak of them, they are more than can be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The conſideration of the eminent acts of God's gracious Providence towards the Church of the Jews, under the Old Teſtament, is a proof of this truth; ſome few whereof are theſe. 1. Of all Nations under Heaven them only he ſeparated, to be a holy People for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Deut. 7.6, 7, 8. <hi>Thou art a holy people unto the Lord thy God; the Lord thy God hath choſen thee to be a ſpecial people for himſelf, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the people that are upon the face of the earth; the Lord did not ſet his love upon you, nor chuſe you, becauſe ye were more in number than any other people, for ye were the feweſt of all people, but becauſe the Lord loveth you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Deliverance, ſo miraculou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly wrought for them, was an eminent act of God's good Providence to them, and that in theſe reſpects. 1. He furniſhed them with a General every way fit for that Expedition, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 105.26. <hi>He ſent Moſes his ſervant and Aaron whom he had choſen.</hi> 2. He inflicted ten ſeveral tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendous Plagues and fearful Judgments on their perſecuting and oppreſſive Enemies, becauſe they would not allow them liberty to worſhip God according to the Command of God and their own Conſciences. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 105.27. That of the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off all the Firſt-Born of their Adverſaries in one night, when the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>oying Angel paſs'd over them, is memorable; as alſo their being in <hi>Goſhen,</hi> a Land of Light for three days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when the other were in Darkneſs. 3. In ſpite of all Oppoſers, they had one very glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Sacramental Paſſover-day, before they were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59023:7"/>brought forth. 4. He did greatly enrich them with Ear-rings and Jewels of their cruel Task-maſters, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.36. 5. While they were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with the Red Sea, on the one hand, and <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Army on the other, you know what great Salvation he wrought for them. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>O ſing unto the Lord for he hath triumphed gloriouſly, the horſe and his rider hath he thrown into the Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The many ſignal paſſages of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence towards them in the Wilderneſs, do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate this Truth, Truly God is good to <hi>Iſrael.</hi> 1. He ſweetned the bitter Waters of <hi>Marah</hi> for them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.23, 24, 25. 2. He Rained Manna from Heaven upon them, and gave them Quails to eat, even when in a pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh murmuring Humour, they ſaid unto <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> would to God we had Died by the Hand of the Lord in the Land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> when we ſat by the fleſh-Pots, and when we did eat Bread to the full, for ye have brought us forth into the Wilderneſs to kill the whole Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with Hunger. 3. When they Thirſted and had no Drink, <hi>He opened the Rock, and the Waters guſhed out, they ran in the dry places like a River,</hi> Pſal. 105.41. 4. Through the preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Prayer, they obtained a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Victory over the <hi>Amalekites, Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur,</hi> holding up his Hands, for which an Altar was errected to the Lord as an eternal Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17. end. 5. They had the Pillar of the Cloud by Day to keep them from the violence and ſcorching Heat of the Sun, and the Pillar of Fire by Night to ſhelter them from the cold thereof, and to lead them on their way in the Dark, <hi>Pſ.</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59023:7"/>105.39. 6. They had the Law in a moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn way and manner given forth from Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> Exod. 20. O happy is that People that's under a Theocracy, and who are governed only by that Law which is purely Divine: The Law Moral, did in a general way teach them their Duty both to God and Man. The Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial did teach them more particularly what to give unto God, and the judicial Law did inform them how they ought to walk one towards another as Members of ſuch a Body Politick, Nation, Kingdom, or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. 7. The Lord did inſtitute Tabernacle-Worſhip firſt in the Wilderneſs: Better be in the Wilderneſs with God's Ordinances, than in <hi>Aegypt</hi> without them. 8. When they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Idolatrous in erecting a Molten Calf, to be a viſible repreſentation of God's march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on before them, upon their Repentance and <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Prayer, God was graciouſly pleaſed to pardon their Sin, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.11, 12, 13, 14, 9. All that Forty Years they were in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, they had no need to renew their Shooes nor Garments. 10. When they were ſtung with fiery Serpents, they had a brazen Serpent erected, as an Ordinance of divine Inſtitution for their Remedy and Cure, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.9. Laſtly, Moſt of all theſe things, their Manna, Water out of the Rock, Tabernacles, high Prieſt, Ark, Sacrifices, Altars, Pillar of the Cloud, and Fire, and the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Serpent, were Typical repreſentations of Jeſus Chriſt, and viſible Signs of his Preſence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. I was lately very much taken with the Reading of the Firſt, Second, Third and Fourth Chapters of <hi>Numbers,</hi> where after numbring the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they are Ranked
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59023:8"/>in Battalia as a Camp; in the midſt of this Camp was the Tabernacle, with the Ark of the Covenant; next unto it the Prieſts and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, and round about them, the reſt of the Tribes; when the Prieſts and Levites ſtood with the Ark, the People ſtood, when the Ark moved and marched on, they accordingly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed; and what did all this ſignifie? But that they were even in the Wilderneſs, under the conduct of their great Captain-General Jeſus Chriſt, Deut. 32.11, 12, 13. <hi>As an Eagle ſtirreth up her neſt, and fluttereth over her Young, ſpreadeth abroad her wings. So the Lord alone did lead him, and there was no ſtrange God with him, he made him ride on high places of the earth, that he might eat the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the fields, and he made him to ſuck honey out of the Rock, and oyl out of the ſtinty rock.</hi> Gen. 32.34. Behold mine Angel ſhall go before thee; it was in Alluſion to this march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Poſture of their's, that the Pſalmiſt breaks forth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46. Though the Mountains be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, the Lord of Hoſts is with us, the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> is our Refuge, God is in the midſt of her, ſhe ſhall not be moved. And <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Who is ſhe that looketh forth as the Morning, fair as the Moon, clear as the Sun, terrible as an Army with banners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Time would fail in telling you what God did in dividing <hi>Jordan,</hi> in poſſeſſing them with a Land that did flow with Milk and Honey, in diſtributing to every Tribe their Portion and Inheritance, by lot, in driving out their Enemies, the <hi>Ammonites Moabites,</hi> the <hi>Hivites, Jebuſites</hi> and <hi>Gargaſites,</hi> what ſhall I tell you of his raiſing up <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak, Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59023:8"/>Sampſon, Ely, Samuel</hi> and others en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with an extraordinary Spirit, to be not only Princes and Judges over them, but alſo to reſcue them out of the Hands of their Enemies, to whom their Sins had enſlaved them, what ſhall I tell you of all the gracious acts of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour conferred upon them under the good Kings, <hi>David, Solomon, Aſa, Jehoſaphat, Hezekiah, Joſiah?</hi> O how good was God to them, even in <hi>Babylon:</hi> How many of them were kept faithful in the worſt times, he ſent extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prophets to Preach Repentance to them after they had revolted. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> were commiſſioned to propheſy their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from the Babyloniſh Captivity, <hi>Daniel</hi> prayed for it. O how miraculouſly were they preſerved from <hi>Haman</hi>'s bloody Conſpiracy and intended Maſſacre, in <hi>Eſther</hi> and <hi>Mordecai</hi>'s time. O how they were preſerved in <hi>Daniel</hi>'s time, notwithſtanding of that tyrannical Edict and Decree, That whoſoever would not fall down before their abominable idolatrous Image, ſhould be thrown into the Fiery Furnace. O the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God to them in ſtirring up the Spirit of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and <hi>Ezra</hi> for rebuilding the Temple. O the goodneſs of God, in raiſing <hi>Cyrus</hi> to be ſo favourable to them, as to grant their deſire, and give them all due Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to go on in the Work of the Lord. If I ſhould proceed to particulars here, I ſhould not know where to make an end: The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of God to them in <hi>Aegypt</hi> may be known from the 15th Chap. of <hi>Exod.</hi> the 78.105. and 106. <hi>Pſalms</hi> with the 7th Chap. of the <hi>Acts.</hi> If you would know God's goodneſs to them under the Judges and Kings, Read
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59023:9"/>
               <hi>Joſhua, Judges, Samuel, Kings</hi> and <hi>Chronicles:</hi> If while in <hi>Babylon,</hi> Read <hi>Eſther, Ezra</hi> and <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah:</hi> after the deliverance Read the Books commonly called Apocrypha, to which we may give an Hiſtorical Faith, as to any other Hiſtories. O how gloriouſly good was God in raiſing up <hi>Judas Maccabeus</hi> to reſcue his Brethren and People from the cruel Tyranny of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes.</hi> A ſhort Epitome and Summary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capitulation of all you have, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4, 5. Who are <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to whom pertaineth the Adoption, they were the only Children of God, and the Glory, <hi>i. e.</hi> either all that Glory whereby God exalted them above others in reſpect of many miraculous Deliverances, or the Ark of the Covenant ſo called, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.21, 22. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Cherubims of Glory covered it, as alſo it was a Shadow and Figure of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Glory and Majeſty of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.8, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.5. And the Covenants, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Tables of the Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.4. And the Lawgiving, <hi>i. e.</hi> the judicial Law, the former being underſtood of the Moral; and the Service of God, <hi>i. e.</hi> his Worſhip which was firſt Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in the Tabernacle, afterwards in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple, and the promiſes, to wit of ſending the Meſſiah, and with him all other Bleſſings and Benefits, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. whoſe are the Fathers, <hi>i. e.</hi> they were deſcended of the Patriarchs, and the Fathers are of them, and of whom Chriſt is for as much as concern the Fleſh, who is God over all, Bleſſed for ever, Amen.</p>
            <p>Before I proceed, I would have you make this uſe of what has been ſaid. 1. Was God ſo good to his People of Old? And is not he
<pb facs="tcp:59023:9"/>the ſame ſtill, Yeſterday, to Day, and for evermore? Truſt in the Lord and do good, and verily thou ſhalt be fed as well as they, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.3. The Mercy of the Lord endureth for ever. 2. When the Lord's peculiar ones provoked him with their Sins, they were not privileged with an exemption from Puniſhments, as we may ſee at this Day: Let us learn to ſtand in awe, and fear to offend. This very uſe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> makes of this point, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20, 21, 22, 23. <hi>Becauſe of unbelief they were broken off, and thou ſtandeſt by Faith: Be not high minded, but fear: For if God ſpared not the natural branches, take heed leſt he alſo ſpare not thee: Behold therefore the goodneſs and ſeverity of God on them which fell, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but towards thee, goodneſs if thou continue in his goodneſs; otherwiſe thou alſo ſhalt be cut off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, God's goodneſs to his Goſpel-Church far exceeds his goodneſs to them of old. 1. Goſpel-Converts are far more numerous than formerly; the <hi>Jews</hi> and their Proſelytes were but very few in compariſon of all the reſt of the World then, and of Goſpel-Converts now. For now there are Thouſands in <hi>Germany,</hi> Thouſands in <hi>France,</hi> Thouſands in <hi>Britaine, Netherlands.</hi> 2. Chriſt himſelf is now actually come, Dead, Riſen, Aſcended and Glorified, and therefore the Glory of the latter Houſe, is greater than that of the former, <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.9. They were promiſed that he ſhould come, and were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to believe on him, which made honeſt <hi>Abraham</hi> ſo to rejoyce in ſeeing his Day, though but a far off. O how good is the Lord then to us, whoſe lot is fallen under
<pb facs="tcp:59023:10"/>this diſpenſation of Grace, where we may clearly diſcern, that the work of reconciliation between God and us, is perfectly accompliſhed, Divine Juſtice is ſatisfied to the full, and all our Enemies ſo far conquered, that they cannot in the leaſt injure us. 3. God hath delivered us from the Ceremonies of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law; a Yoak that neither they nor their Fathers were well able to bear, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10. Their Ceremonies were ſo many, and each of them ſignificant, that it was a great burden to their Memories to remember all: They were alſo very coſtly and chargeably, they muſt kill many Lambs, Goats, Bullocks, keep ſeveral ſolemn Feſtivals, and all at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but now the goodneſs of God to us is in this, that he does not put us upon any ſuch tedious Journies, he does not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſuch chargeable Sacrifices of us, not ſo limit his Worſhip to any one place, but it is as acceptable in one as another, <hi>John</hi> 4.24, 25. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8. Deliverance from the Ceremonial Law, is an act of favour to us; upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count alſo, that it was a Wall of ſeparation, in a viſible way to diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Jews</hi> and us, to ſignify that they were the People of God and we not, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.14. 4. Their Ordinances were comparatively car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10. Which ſtood only in Meats and Drinks and Waſhings, and were impoſed on them till the time of Reformation; ours are far more Spiritual; they had many Sacraments, to wit Manna, the Rock, the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of the Cloud, brazen Serpent, Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the paſchal Lamb, in ſtead of all theſe, we have only Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper. 5. Though the Covenant, under which they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59023:10"/>were, and we are, be the ſame for ſubſtance, yet in reſpect of the diverſity of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, our mercy far exceeds theirs. 1. Their Covenant was in a more legal ſtrain than ours, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.5, 6. <hi>Moſes</hi> deſcribeth the Righteouſneſs which is of the Law, <hi>That the Man which doth theſe things ſhall live by them, but the Righteouſneſs which is of Faith, ſpeaketh on this wiſe, Say not in thine Heart who ſhall aſcend—the word is nigh thee, even in thy Mouth, and in thine Heart, that if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy Mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt believe in thine Heart, that God hath raiſed him from the Dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi> 2. Their's was adminiſtred by the Hands of <hi>Moſes,</hi> a typical Mediator on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ours by Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>God who at ſundry times, and in divers manners, ſpake in time paſt unto the Fathers by the Prophets, hath in theſe loſt Days ſpoke unto us by his Son, whom he hath appointed heir of all things.</hi> 3. The diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation they were under, was full of Dread, Horrour and Terror, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. end. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. When the Law was given forth from <hi>Sinai,</hi> the Mount was all in a Fire, to point at the hot burning Wrath they might look for, in caſe they were found tranſgreſſors; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur's from Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> is full of Meekneſs, Gentleneſs, Mercy and Love. St. <hi>John, If ye love me keep my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</hi> 4. The promiſes of our Covenant are better than theirs; if they did obſerve the Statutes and Ordinances of God, they might warrantably expect to be bleſt in their Basket and Store, and ſuch other temporal things, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. But now though we
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59023:11"/>cannot by vertue of a promiſe expect bleſſings of this kind upon our obſervation of Divine Precepts, but rather the contrary, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. <hi>Whoever will be my Diſciple muſt deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, take up his Croſs, and follow me.</hi> And <hi>Acts</hi> 4. <hi>Through manifold Temptations or Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, we muſt all enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> And 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. <hi>All that will live Godly in Chriſt Jeſus, muſt ſuffer Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſection;</hi> yet we may expect Spiritual Bleſſings, and that in a greater meaſure than they. 1. We are promiſed greater plenty of Spiritual Knowledge than they. That of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.9. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to goſpel-Times. <hi>The Earth ſhall be full of the Knowledge of the Lord, as the Waters cover the Sea.</hi> And 35.5. <hi>Then ſhall the eyes of the blind be opened, and the ears of the deaf be unſtopped.</hi> And 32.3, 4. And 42.16. <hi>I will bring the blind by a way they know not, I will lead them in paths they have not known: I will make darkneſs light before them, and crooked things ſtrait. Theſe things will I do unto them, and not forſake them.</hi> 2 Cor. 3.15, 16, 18. And 4.3. The Preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is not Darkned with Types, Figures and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies as in the Days of old. 2. Spiritual Fruitfulneſs is promiſed to us, <hi>Matth</hi> 21.41. <hi>The Kingdom of God ſhall be taken from you Jews, and given to a Nation bringing forth the Fruits thereof. Iſa.</hi> 35.7, 8. <hi>In the wilderneſs ſhall waters break out, and ſtreams in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, and the parched ground ſhall become a pool, and the thirſty land Springs of water; in the habitation of dragons, where each lay, ſhall be reeds and ruſhes.</hi> 3. Spiritual peace, joy and comfort is promiſed to our Days, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.17.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59023:11"/>The Work of Righteouſneſs ſhall be peace, and the effect of Righteouſneſs quietneſs and aſſurance for ever, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. Begin: <hi>Being juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Faith, we have Peace with God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, by whom alſo we have acceſs by Faith into this Grace wherein we ſtand and rejoyce in hope of the Glory of God, and not only ſo, but we Glory in Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation alſo, knowing that Tribulation work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Patience, and Patience Experience, and Experience Hope, and Hope maketh not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, becauſe the Love of God is ſhed abroad into our Hearts by the holy Ghoſt.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>In whom believing ye rejoyce with a joy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable and full of Glory.</hi> 4. We have the promiſe of the Spirit more than they, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. <hi>I will pour out my Spirit upon all Fleſh. Acts</hi> 2.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.3. O how good is the Lord to us in this reſpect, if we are not wanting to our ſelves through unbelief; the diſpenſation under which we are, promiſes the pourings forth of the Spirit to us, O! who are we that we ſhould be thus dealt by?</p>
            <p>Let's make ſome uſe of what has been ſaid as to this head, and ſo I go on.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let Men and Angels be ſummoned in to admire and adore, let our Souls and all that's within us, Extoll and Magnifie the rich Grace and Goodneſs of this God, that has caſt off his Ancient People, and has taken us gentile ſinners, who were Aliens from the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and Strangers to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and made us heirs of the promiſes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17. O the depth of the Riches both of the Wiſdom and Knowledge of God, how unſearchable are his Judgments and his Ways
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59023:12"/>paſt finding out! O what are we poor wild Olives, that we ſhould be grafted in amongſt the Natural Branches, and partake of the fatneſs of the Olives! O bleſſed are your Eyes and Ears which ſee and hear ſuch things as were denyed many of the Fathers! See <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10. <hi>Acts</hi> 28. end. O how good is this God that has inveſted every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church of gentile Believers, with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter privileges than their National Church had, and private Chriſtians are in ſome reſpects privileged beyond their Church Officers, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.4. He hath made us Kings and Prieſts to God, to offer up Spiritual Sacrifices of Praiſe and Thankſgiving to him through Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Study to walk worthy of this goodneſs of the Lord unto all well-pleaſing, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. Let every Soul ſay, O what ſhall I render to the Lord. 1. Take heed thou doſt not live in any the leaſt Sin; beware of Ignorance; if any thing prove the Condemnation of the World, it will be this, <hi>That light is come, and they de light in darkneſs more than in light,</hi> John 3.19. We may now ſay, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3. If our Goſpel be hid, it's hid to them that Periſh. beware of unbelief, <hi>John</hi> 3.18. <hi>He that believeth not on him, is condemned already, becauſe he hath not believed in the Name of the only begotten Son of God.</hi> O beware of ingratitude, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace into Wantonneſs, <hi>Jude</hi> 4. There are certain Men who were before of old ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Condemnation, ungodly Men turning the Grace of God into Laſciviouſneſs—Say rather <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Shall I Sin becauſe I am under Grace? God forbid.</hi> 2. Think it not enough to abſtain from Sin, and to have true Grace, but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59023:12"/>that your Graces may in ſome meaſure be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the Covenant you are under; has God been pleaſed to make great promiſes, and wilt not thou labour for ſuch a Faith as may apply theſe promiſes according to their full Latitude and extent? Has God now manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Riches of his Grace in reconciling the World to himſelf, through his Son, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring alſo, that whoſoever will believe on him ſhall be ſaved? And why art thou ſtill in a doubting and queſtioning Condition? 3. Lay out your ſelves in glorifying this good God, eſpecially in theſe two. 1. In a Goſpel-Frame of Spirit, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Put on therefore as the Elect of God, dearly and beloved bowels of Mercies, kindneſs, Humbleneſs of Mind, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, long-Suffering, forbearing one another and forgiving one another: If any Man have a quarrel againſt any, even as Chriſt forgave you, ſo alſo do ye, and above all theſe things put on Charity, which is the Bond of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and let the Peace of God Rule in your Hearts; to the which alſo ye were called in one Body and be ye thankful.</hi> 2. In a Goſpel-Converſation, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12, 13, 14. <hi>The Night is far ſpent, the day is at hand, let us therefore caſt off the works of darkneſs, and lets us put on the armour of light, let us walk honeſtly, as in the day, not in rioting and drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs, not in ſtrife and envying, not in Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering and wantonneſs, but put ye on the Lord Jeſus.</hi> 4. Take all in good part that comes from the Hands of a good God. Learn Contentation with a ſuffering Condition, and a perſecuted State: Live by Faith on the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made to perſons in ſuch a Condition,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59023:13"/>
               <hi>John</hi> 16.33. <hi>In the World ye ſhall have tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, but be of good chear, I have overcome the World. Mark</hi> 10.29, 30. <hi>Jeſus ſaith unto them, verily I ſay unto you, there is no Man that hath left houſe, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands, for my ſake and the goſpels, but he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an hundred-fold in this time, houſes, and brethren, and ſiſters, and mothers, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and lands, with perſecutions; and in the world to come eternal life.</hi> Matth. 5.10, 11. <hi>Bleſſed are they which are perſecuted for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſake, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven, bleſſed are ye, when Men ſhall revile you, and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of evil of you falſely for my ſake. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in heaven, ſo perſecuted they the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets which were before you.</hi> 1 Pet. 4.14. <hi>If ye are reproached for the Name of Chriſt, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py are ye, for the Spirit of Glory and of God reſteth upon you, on their part he is evil ſpoken of, but on your part he is glorified.</hi> And 16, 17, 18. <hi>If any Man ſuffer as a Chriſtian, let him not be aſhamed, but let him glorifie God on this behalf, for the time is come that judgment muſt begin at the Houſe of God, and if it firſt begin at us, what ſhall the end be of them that obey not the Goſpel of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let them that ſuffer according to the Will of God, commit the keeping of their Souls to him in well-doing, as unto a faithful Creator.</hi> And 5.10. <hi>But the God of all grace, who hath called us unto his eternal glory by Jeſus Chriſt, after that ye have ſuffered a while, make ye perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen, ſettle you.</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:59023:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>2 Tim. 1.12. <hi>For the Goſpel of Chiſt I ſuffer theſe things, nevertheleſs I am not aſhamed, for I know whom I have believed, and I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that he is able to keep that which I have committed unto him againſt that day.</hi> And 2.10, 11, 12. <hi>Therefore I endure all for the elects ſake, that they may alſo obtain the ſalvation, which is in Chriſt Jeſus, with eternal glory. It is a faithful ſaying, If we be dead with him, we ſhall alſo live with him, if we ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo reign with him.</hi> Rom. 8.17, 18, 35, 36. 2 Cor. 4.17, 18. Laſtly, Study a thankfull improvement of your privileges for all God's goodneſs towards your. 1. Seeing it coſt Chriſt no leſs than his precious Blood to purchaſe a liberty for you, from the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaical Ceremonies, which were once of Divine Inſtitution, and conſequently much more from ſuch as are of meer humane inſtitution, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Heatheniſh or Antichriſtian, you ought not upon any pretence whatſoever, ſuffer your ſelves to be intangled again with that Yoak of Bondage: There's a great noiſe about the Churches Power to impoſe Ceremonies, in matters indifferent; but I dare be bold to ſay, if there be ſuch a thing in the World as Chriſtian Liberty in any thing, it is not to be impoſed upon in Ceremonies; and if any thing be a lording it over the Lord's heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage it is in not leaving thoſe things indifferent which Chriſt hath left indifferent. Chriſtian Liberty is not eaſily to be parted with, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it coſt Chriſt ſo dear. 2. All that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatory fulneſs of Grace and Spirit that's in Jeſus Chriſt, is freely made over to us, let's therefore improve this privilege, ſo as every
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59023:14"/>moment upon all occaſions to be ſtill fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſupplies for our Soul-wants: From this overflowing Fountain, ſay thus, Lord, I want Wiſdom, Faith, Patience, Power againſt Corruptions, Temptations, Enemies — <hi>in my Fleſh dwells no good thing;</hi> but oh, is there not Goodneſs and Grace enough in thee; and is not this Goodneſs of thine communicable; <hi>Out of thy Son's fulneſs let me receive grace for grace,</hi> Joh. 1.16. 3. Through that new and living way, we have liberty of acceſs to the throne of Grace. Let us accordingly improve this Privilege, in coming with a full aſſurance of Faith, to find grace and help in time of need: Let's come with a Child like confidence; with a holy and humble boldneſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. end, and 4. end, and 10.22, 23, 24. 4. Through God's graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Goodneſs, we are made joint heirs with Chriſt, his Bleſſings, Benefits, Death and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, are all ours; improve this Privilege to a deliverance from ſlaviſh fears. If Chriſt hath triumphed over Principalities and Powers, Sin and Satan, Death and the World, what is Man, O Goſpel Saint, that thou art afraid of him; if he has purchaſed pardon of Sin, peace of Conſcience, the Joys of the Holy Ghoſt, Grace here, and Heaven's Glory hereafter, thou need'ſt not fear that the Powers of Hell ſhall be able to deprive thee thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> God was very good to the primitive Church in the days of Chriſt and the Apoſtles, and that in theſe reſpects. 1. He did, as it were from Heaven, give an immediate Call and extraordinary Commiſſion to <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> to be the Harbinger and For-runner of the Son of God and Saviour of the World. It was he that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59023:14"/>firſt brought into the World the good news of the near approach of the Kingdom of Heaven, which did call aloud upon them to Repent, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.2. The aggravation of the Mercy was in the ſeaſonableneſs of it, he was ſent at ſuch a time, when the Church was ſo deeply cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, that there was hardly the face of a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church to be ſeen upon them. See further of him, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 40.3. <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.5, 6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.7, 8,9. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.8. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.16. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11, 12. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.14. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.15, 16, 17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The primitive Church was honour'd with Chriſt's own corporal Preſence amongſt them; hence they were called the Children of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom; and it could not but be a day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing to them, to hear the Bridgroom's voice. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.29. <hi>Mark</hi> 2.19. When that good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> heard of the Salutation of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> the Babe leaped in her Womb, and the was filled with the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.41. <hi>Mary</hi> her ſelf broke forth into a Doxology and Song of praiſes, which you may ſee <hi>Luke</hi> 1.46. to 55. <hi>Zacharias</hi> alſo was filled with the Holy Ghoſt, and Propheſied, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael, for he hath viſited and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed his people; he hath raiſed up a born of Salvation for us in the houſe of David, as he ſpake by the mouth of his holy Prophets, which have been ſince the world began.</hi> — The very Angels in Heaven thought it not too mean an Employment for them, to bring this Meſſage to the Shepherds. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.8, 9, 10. <hi>Fear not, for, behold, I bring you good tydings of great joy which ſhall be to all people; for unto you is born this day, in the City of David, a Saviour, which is Chriſt the Lord,</hi> verſe 13.14. <hi>And ſuddenly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59023:15"/>there was with the Angel a multitude of the heavenly hoſt, praiſing God, and ſaying, Glory to God in the higheſt, and on earth peace, good will towards men:</hi> And that good old Man, <hi>Simeon,</hi> verſe 28, 29. <hi>When he had ſeen the Child, Jeſus, he took him up in is Arms, and bleſſed God, ſaying, Now letteſt thou thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant depart in peace according to thy word, for mine eyes have ſeen thy Salvation — a light to lighten the Gentiles, and the glory of they people Iſrael.</hi> Chriſt himſelf being come, they might now know, that God was a great Lover of Mankind; now they had an ample proof of his faithfulneſs, in making good what he had long before promiſed: Now they might be ſure that Shadows would flee away, the Subſtance being come: Now they might be aſſured of the downfal of the Devil's Kingdom; witneſs the ſilencing the Oracles of <hi>Jupiter, Apollo,</hi> and <hi>Hecate;</hi> as alſo the locking up the Temple of <hi>Janus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. God's goodneſs to the primitive Church, was in furniſhing them with Paſtors according to his own Heart; the greatneſs of which Mercy may appear from the Conſideration of theſe Circumſtances. 1. The number of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church-Officers was perfect and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat for ſpecies and kind, there was none wanting which her Condition did then call for. Of extraordinary Officers there were Twelve Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.1. Seventy Evangeliſts; particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Churches had their ordinary Officers, to wit, Biſhops, <hi>i. e.</hi> Paſtors and Teachers, to whom the Adminiſtration of Ordinances, and Overſight of the Flock was committed, Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters or Elders, who were to look to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59023:15"/>Manners, and Government of the Church, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. And Deacons, who were to take care of the Poor, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. <hi>begin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 2. There was then a parity and equality of all Officers in their kinds: Amongſt the Apoſtles, none claimed a Superiority over the reſt: <hi>Peter</hi>'s Supremacy was then unknown; as the Keys of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven were given to him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.19. ſo alſo to the reſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.23. The very affectation of pre-eminence, was, in thoſe days, diſtaſtful to Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.1, 2, 3, 4. and 20.25, 26, <hi>Jeſus called them unto him, and ſaid, Ye know that the Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe dominion over them, but it ſhall not be ſo among you; but whoſoever will be great among you, let him be your Miniſter; and whoſoever will be chief among you, let him be you Servant; even as the Son of man came not to be miniſtred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but to miniſter.</hi> — And as it was diſtaſtful to Chriſt, ſo alſo to themſelves. <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.21, 22, 23, 24. <hi>When the ten heard what the Mother of Zebedee</hi>'s <hi>Children had asked for her two Sons, they were moved with indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt them:</hi> And as one Apoſtle was not over the reſt of the Apoſtles, ſo there was a parity between Biſhops and Presbyters, <hi>i. e.</hi> ordinary Preaching and Ruling Officers or El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; they were not two diſtinct Offices nor Officers; as may appear from <hi>Act.</hi> 20.17. with 28. whom he had called Presbyters <hi>v.</hi> 17. he calls Biſhops <hi>v.</hi> 28. 2. From <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.1. he directs the Epiſtle to the Biſhops and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons: <hi>Philippi</hi> being but a City, it cannot be imagin'd that there were Metropolitan of Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan Biſhops, in the plural number, in it; therefore the Biſhops there ſpoken of, were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59023:16"/>ordinary Church Officers: This is the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> on the Text. 3. From <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. with 7. <hi>For this cauſe left I thee in Crete to ordain Presbyters;</hi> for a Biſhop muſt be blameleſs — This <hi>for</hi> muſt either be a reaſon of what is in the preceding verſe, or it ſignifies nothing; the qualifications required in both are the ſame, therefore they are not diſtinct Officers. 4. From 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, 2. The Apoſtle exhorts the Presbyters to watch over their Flocks — <hi>v.</hi> 5. taking the overſight of them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoping it over them: The Work of both is the ſame, and therefore the Office is the ſame. 5. From <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12. where all ſorts of Officers, both extraordinary and ordinary, are reckon'd; and if Lord Prelates be neither Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Evangeliſts, Prophets, Paſtors, nor Tech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, They are none of Chriſt's Creatures, but of Humane Inſtitution. 6. From 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. to <hi>v.</hi> 8 begin. where the Apoſtle gives Rules for the Examination and Ordination of a Biſhop, and then immediately he paſſes to the Office of a Deacon, without ſo much as mentioning any thing of a Presbyter; as taking it for granted, that Biſhop and Presbyter were one and the ſame, the Rules for Examination and Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of both are the ſame. And thus you ſee God was good to the Primitive Church, in giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſuch Officers, as did neither Lord it over one another, nor over the Lord's Heritage. A Third circumſtance of this Mercy, was, the extent of the Apoſtolical Commiſſion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. <hi>Go Preach the Goſpel to all the World;</hi> whereas formerly it was confin'd within the compaſs of the Land of <hi>Judea;</hi> ſuch is the goodneſs of God to the Sons of Men now, that he is not willing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59023:16"/>any ſhould periſh, but all ſhould come to the knowledge of the Truth. See <hi>Act.</hi> 10.28, 34, 35. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.47. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.8. and 20.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4, 5. 4. He did furniſh the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles with variety of eminent Gifts and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſuitable to their Work; they had ſuch a Gift of Preaching, that they needed not Read or Study, but they ſpake by immediate Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.11, 12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.3. At one of their Sermons three Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand were Converted, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41. At another five Thouſand, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.4. They had a Spirit of Prayer, they needed not a Book to read a Prayer by a ſet form: They had the Giſt of working Miracles, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.8. By laying on of hands they could confer the gift of the Holy Ghoſt upon others, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.17. and 10.44. and 19.6. In matters of Faith, that concerned the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sinners, and the Church's Edification, they were acted by a Spirit of infallibility, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.13. They could inflict corporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon notorious Hypocrites and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.9, 10. and 13.11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6. They were endued with a prophetical Spirit, whereby they could foretel things to come, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5, 26. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.2. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.13. The whole Book of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> is prophetical.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider the Church it ſelf, and God's goodneſs was great to them in theſe reſpects. 1. Of Ordinances. 2. Order and Government. 3. Of the Purity and Simplicity of the Truth in thoſe days. 4. Of their Gifts. 5. Their Graces. 6. Perſeverance. 7. Sufferings. 1ſt. They had no Ordinances but what were of Divine Inſtitution; theſe alſo were divinely Adminiſtred; and a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59023:17"/>Preſence of God was that, that did high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beautifie all their Adminiſtrations. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.31. <hi>When they had prayed, the place was ſhaken where they were aſſembled, and they were all filled with the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Rev. 1.12, 14. <hi>In the midſt of the ſeven golden candleſticks was one like unto the Son of man, cloathed with a Garment down to the foot, and girt about the paps with a golden girdle,</hi> i. e. Jeſus Chriſt who in reſpect of his Prieſtly Office had a tender Heart, and was both willing and ready to do them good. <hi>His head and his hair were white like wool;</hi> as <hi>white as ſnow, and his eyes were as a flame of fire,</hi> i. e. In reſpect of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical Office, he did ſhew himſelf, in all their Church-Adminiſtrations, to be full of Wiſdom, Gravity, Prudence, and Underſtanding; <hi>And his feet like unto fine braſs, as if they burned in a furnace; and his voice was as the voice of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waters,</hi> i, e. He did triumphantly conquer many ſtout-hearted and rebellious Sinners, by virtue of his Kingly Power and Regal Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in his Ordinances, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 110.3, 4. and 45.</p>
            <p>2dly, God was good in reſpect of that good Order, Diſcipline and Government that was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them: Chriſt himſelf was their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign and Supreme Law-giver in all Church-matters, according to what was Propheſied, <hi>Is.</hi> 9.6, 7. <hi>The government ſhall be upon his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders:</hi> Zech. 6.13. <hi>Even he ſhall build the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord, and he ſhall bear the glory; and he ſhall ſit and rule upon his throne.</hi> The Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven were put in the hands of thoſe that were faithful: Of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> Matth. 16.19. Of all the Apoſtles, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. Of the whole Church, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17, 18. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59023:17"/>was their Order and Polity; that Church-Officers medled only with what was proper for them, to wit, the Authoritative exerciſe of Church Power; and the Church medled with nothing but what was proper for them. In the Primitive Church, during the firſt Century, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was done <hi>ſine conſenſu plebis,</hi> without the conſent of the People, as Mr. <hi>Jacob</hi> proves by an hundred Teſtimonies out of the pureſt Antiquity, they had the power of chooſing their own Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. <hi>end,</hi> and 6. <hi>begin.</hi> Of admitting Members, as in the caſe of <hi>Saul</hi>'s ſeeking to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join himſelf, who was hindred by the Brethren of the Church, till they received ſatisfaction from <hi>Barnabas</hi>'s. <hi>Act.</hi> Of caſting out offending Members, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. Of re-admitting Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate Penitents, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. Their order was, that no particular Church did arrogate Power or Juriſdiction over other particular Churches; the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi>'s ſending to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Act. 15. to conſult with them concerning ſome Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal Differences, does argue, That they had full power to determine the matter among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, without making any appeal: their order was, that they did not preſs things indifferent upon ſcrupling Conſciences, as if they had been neceſſary, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. and 9. Chapters: They well knew that to have done otherwiſe, would have been Tyranny, and deſtructive to Chriſtian Liberty; and ſo for many other things.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Primitive Church, in reſpect of purity of Doctrine, was called, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> A Woman that had on her Head a Crown of twelve Stars; however they were branded by their Enemies as Heretical; yet the Doctrine they profeſs'd was purely Apoſtolical. It's true, falſe Teachers did
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59023:18"/>creep in now and then amongſt them, and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſeveral Truths; but, through the vigilance and faithfulneſs of the Servants of God, they were quickly and convincingly confuted: They did teach that we muſt ſeek Righteouſneſs for Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, partly by Chriſt, and partly by the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law; but the Epiſtles to <hi>Coloſſ. Galat.</hi> and <hi>Hebrews</hi> were written againſt this Hereſie. <hi>Cerinthus</hi> denyed the Divinity of Chriſt, for which the Goſpel of <hi>John</hi> was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2, 3. <hi>I am jealous over you with a godly jealouſie; for I have eſpouſed you to one husband, that I may preſent you as a chaſt vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to Chriſt: for I fear left as by any means the ſerpent beguiled Eve through his ſubtilty, ſo your minds ſhould be corrupted from the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city that is in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Herein was the Glory of the Primitive Church, That not only the Officers, but alſo many of their Members, were Men ſingularly qualified with gifts. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5, 7. <hi>By him ye are enriched in every thing; in all utterance, and in all knowledge: So that ye come behind in no Gift.</hi> See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>Act.</hi> 8. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.17. <hi>Theſe ſigns ſhall follow them that believe, in my name ſhall they caſt out Devils; they ſhall ſpeak with new tongues; they ſhall take up ſerpents, and if they drink any deadly thing, it ſhall not hurt them, they ſhall lay hands on the ſick and they ſhall recover.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. God was good to them in reſpect of Grace: <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.14. <hi>And I my ſelf am perſwaded of you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that ye are full of goodneſs.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>being confident of this very thing, that he which hath begun a good work in you will perform it until the day of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: even as it is meet for me to think
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59023:18"/>this of you all, becauſe I have you in my heart, in as much as both in my bonds, and in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and confirmation of the Goſpel ye are all partakers of my grace: and this I pray, that your love may yet more and more abound in all knowledge, and in all judgment.</hi> Col. 1.3, 4. <hi>We give thanks unto God—ſince we heard of your Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, and of the love which ye have to all the Saints.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membering without ceaſing, your work of Faith, your labour of love, and patience of hope in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in the ſight of God and of our Father; knowing, brethren beloved, your election of God.</hi> It was no ſmall part of their Glory that they did ſo abound in Love, which did evidence it ſelf in two notable Acts 1. They kept the unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace; though ſome were for Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, others againſt it; ſome for obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Days, Ceremonies, eating Meats, and others not, yet they did in a great meaſure live in Love and Unity, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32. <hi>The mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of them that believed, were of one Heart, and of one Soul.</hi> 2. There was none of them wanted neceſſaries ſo long as others had wherewithall to ſupply them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.12, 13, 14. <hi>The adminiſtration of this ſervice, not only ſupplieth the want of the Saints, but is abundant alſo, by many thanksgivings unto God; whiles by the experiment of this Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration they glorifie God for your profeſſed ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection unto the goſpel of Chriſt, and for your liberal diſtribution unto them, and unto all Men: And by their prayer for you, which long after you, for the exceeding grace of God in you: Thanks be unto God for his unſpeakable gift.</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:59023:19"/>Rom. 15.25, 26, 27. <hi>I go to Jeruſalem to miniſter to the Saints, for it hath pleaſed them of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia and Achaia, to make a certain contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution for the poor Saints which are at Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, it hath pleaſed them verily and their debtors they are: For if the Gentiles have been partakers of their ſpiritual things, their duty is alſo to Miniſter unto them in carnal things.</hi> Acts 2.44, 45. <hi>All that believed were to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and had all things common, and ſold their poſſeſſions and goods, and parted them to all Men, as every Man had need.</hi> And 4.32. <hi>Neither ſaid any of them that ought of the things which he poſſeſſed was his own, but they had all things common.</hi> 6. In all Changes and Conditions, they were conſtant, ſtill one and the ſame, not ſickle or variable, ſome times for one thing, ſometimes for another, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42. <hi>And they continued ſteadfaſtly in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles doctrine and in fellowſhip, and in breaking of bread and in prayers.</hi> 46.47. <hi>And they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued daily in the Temple with one accord, and breaking bread from houſe to houſe, did eat their meat with gladneſs and ſingleneſs of heart, praiſing God, and having favour with all people; and the Lord added to the Church dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch as ſhould be ſaved.</hi> 2 Cor. 1.21, 22. 1 Theſ. 3.12, 13. Rev. 3.10. <hi>Thou haſt kept the word of my patience.</hi> And 2.13. <hi>I know thy works and where thou dwelleſt, even where Satans ſeat is, and holdeſt faſt my Name, and haſt not denied my Faith, even in thoſe days wherein Antipas was my faithful Martyr</hi>—<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Laſtly, The Lord was graciously pleaſed to confer the Honour of Martyrdom upon them: <hi>Stephen</hi> was the Proto-Martyr, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. They
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59023:19"/>were ſcattered at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by reaſon of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution. <hi>Acts.</hi> 8. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> ſuffered at <hi>Rome.</hi> under <hi>Nero;</hi> the one Beheaded, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Crucified: So alſo <hi>James</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Juſtus,</hi> Nay there was not one of the Apoſtles that eſcaped a violent Death, <hi>John</hi> only excepted. Let us make ſome uſe of all this in ſome Three or Four things. 1. Let us bleſs God for his goodneſs to them. O Bleſſed be the Lord that ever there was ſuch a one as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>—O Bleſſed be the Lord for the Truths, Ordinances, Gifts and Graces that were communicated to them; we are in a ſenſe ſharers in the Mercies, What was then writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or tranſacted, ſaid or done, was all for our Inſtruction. 2. Did the Lord give forth ſuch an abundant meaſure of the Spirit, at the firſt Plantation of the Goſpel, according to what the Work of that Day did require, which was to bring the carnal <hi>Jews</hi> from off their Ceremonies, and the heatheniſh <hi>Gentiles</hi> from Satan to God, who muſt ſee Miracles, otherwiſe they will not believe? Let us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and be confident that the ſame good God will not be wanting to proportion the Gifts and Graces of his Churches and Servants to the Work of this our Day, which is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion from Antichriſtianiſm. Bleſſed be the Lord for any ſmall bedewings and beſprinklings of the Spirit poured forth upon any in our times in order hereunto. 3. Let us from hence bemoan our ſelves, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that go under the Name of Churches of Chriſt, who have degenerated ſo far from them in Doctrine, Diſcipline, Worſhip, Gifts, Graces, Holineſs of Converſation, Perſeverance
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59023:20"/>in Sufferings — <hi>contraria mixta ſepoſita clarius eluceſcunt:</hi> In the primitive times Chriſt placed us in a kind of Paradiſe, but we have not kept our firſt Habitation. 4. Let's not only remember whence we are fallen, but alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to our firſt Eſtate, and when we ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a Reformation, whether Perſonal or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical: Let's be ſure to ſet the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Pattern before us, as near as may be: Let's Love as they did, endeavour to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace as they did; continue ſteadfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine, in fellowſhip, in breaking of Bread and Prayers as they did — No ſufferings frighted them from following the Lamb; be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of them in all things, imitable ſo far as they were followers of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> God was good to his Goſpel-<hi>Iſrael,</hi> after the Death of the Apoſtles, till <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi>'s time. And here before I come to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, it will be neceſſary to premiſe theſe few general conſiderations as introductory for the clearing of what is further intended. 1. Be it known to you, that immediately upon the Death of the Apoſtles the Church was in a perſecuted ſtate: It's true, it was ſo in their time, but not as afterwards, when there were publick Laws and Edicts made againſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and profeſſors of the Chriſtian Religion, providence ſo ordering it, that they ſhould have ſome reſpite till the Goſpel and Churches had ſome Plantation. 2. The time of this perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted Condition was Three Hundred Years or thereabouts. 3. The Inſtruments whom the Devil made uſe of for this diabolical Service, were the heathen Emperors of <hi>Rome,</hi> Rev. 12.3.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59023:20"/>The party there combating againſt <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels, Chriſt and his People is thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, <hi>A great red Dragon, having ſeven Heads and ten Horns, and ſeven Crowns upon his Heads.</hi> A Dragon becauſe of his Power, red becauſe of his Cruelty, having ſeven Heads <hi>i. e.</hi> ſeven ſeveral ſorts of Governments in <hi>Rome</hi> heatheniſh, as alſo it was built upon ſeven Hills, having ten Heads with ſeven Crowns thereupon, to diſtinguiſh <hi>Rome</hi>-heathen from <hi>Rome</hi>-Antichriſtian, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.1. That has not only ſeven Heads and ten Horns, but alſo Crowns upon the Horns, to intimate that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt made Kingdoms of thoſe that were but Provinces, during the Dragon's Reign un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the heathen Emperors. 4. Having peruſed ſeveral writers of great Note, both for Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Learning, upon that tranſcendantly high myſtical Scripture, of the Revelation: It's moſt probable as I humbly conceive, that they gueſs right who aſſert that the Seals Chap. 6. hold forth this State of the Church during the firſt three Centuries, of which Ch. 12. to verſe 13. ſeems to be explicatory. 5. In treating of this Subject, I ſhall be neceſſitated to make uſe of Hiſtory, to which I require no more of you but a Hiſtorical Faith: I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it a great Mercy that every Age has had ſome faithful Servants of God, whoſe care it has been to tranſmit to poſterity the memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acts of Divine Providence to his People, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.4. <hi>One generation ſhall praiſe thy works to another, and ſhall declare thy mighty acts, I will ſpeak of the glorious honour of thy Majeſty, and of thy wondrous works.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:59023:21"/>
            <p n="1">1. God was good to them in giving forth this incomparable rich and rare Monument of the Revelation of <hi>John</hi> the Divine, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal ſcope and intendment whereof was, 1. To forewarn them of the near approach of ſuffering times, that ſo they might not be ſurprized, but in a readineſs to encounter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. 2. That they might know what their ſufferings would be, by whom, and of what continuance. 3. That they ſhould be comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and encouraged under all, eſpecially upon this two-fold conſideration. 1. There's no ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings ſhall befall you, but according to the predetermination and fore-appointment of a wiſe God, and loving Father. 2. Let the Churches troubles be what they will, they ſhall have a glorious and an aſſured iſſue; ſeeing this was the good end of God in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting this prophetical Piece of holy Writ to us, that it might be a Lanthorn to our Feet to direct our ſteps in a dark Place: Let's not ſlight this good providence, ſo as not at all to peruſe it; only for the Lord's ſake ſtudy Sobriety, Self-denial, Humility and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituality in your peruſal, and then there will be no great danger, otherwiſe there may, and will <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1, 3. <hi>Bleſſed is he that readeth, and they that hear the words of this prophecy, and keep theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. God's good Providence ſo ordered it, that their ſufferings were for Righteouſneſs ſake, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9. <hi>They were ſlain for the word of God, and for the teſtimony which they held.</hi> Their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony was this, The Devil is not to be Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, nor any other Creature whatſoever. This enraged the Dragon who was then Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59023:21"/>to raiſe a perſecution againſt them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.7. Their Teſtimony was that their preſent way of Worſhip, though practiſed by the Emperors, and eſtabliſhed by the publick Laws of the Empire, yet it was idolatrous, ſinful and deteſtable to God; this enraged the Emperors againſt them; they teſtified that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt was the only Son of God, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the World: The Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to acknowledge his Divinity, till firſt by ſome Act or Law of theirs, it ſhould be ſo approved of and ratified, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21, 22. Herein the <hi>Romans
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> became vain in their imaginations, and their fooliſh Heart was full of darkneſs, when they profeſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be wiſe, they became fools.</hi> From all this it is evident that they ſuffered in a very righteous Cauſe. 2. From this alſo that they refuſed conformity to their way of Worſhip, and would not do any the leaſt thing that might but ſeem to honour their Idols, tho' much ſollicited thereunto, both by promiſes of great rewards on the one hand, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of ſore puniſhments on the other, <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius</hi> a Chriſtian Souldier, with his whole Family, was put to Death, though otherwiſe he had done great ſervice, meerly becauſe he would not on the day of Triumph, Sacrifice with the Emperor. <hi>Diocleſian</hi>'s own Wife be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Chriſtian ſuffered on the ſame account. <hi>Marcus Arethuſius</hi> not only refuſed to build the Idols Temple, which himſelf had pulled down, but alſo chuſed Death rather than to contribute one Farthing towards it: They would not deliver up their Bibles; they would not give ſo much as a Clout or Rag, they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59023:22"/>would not ſo much as throw a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe on their Altars: A certain Chriſtian Souldier would needs carry his Garland in his Hand, when his fellows did wear it on their Heads, in Teſtimony of Honour to their Idols. 3. They ſuffered becauſe they would not perſecute their fellow Chriſtians: A me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable inſtance is of that Chriſtian Legion of Souldiers, who after an excellent Oration made by <hi>Mauritius</hi> their Commander to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Maximinianus,</hi> after they had been twice decimated, were afterwards all of them Slain, upon no other account, but becauſe they would not fall upon their fellows. 4. That they ſuffered for Righteouſneſs ſake; may appear from the many falſe calumnies and accuſations that were brought againſt them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.10. When the Dragon in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Emperors had his deadly Wound, it's thus expreſt, <hi>The accuſer of our brethren is caſt down.</hi> 1. They were accuſed for being Enemies to civil Government upon a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold account. 1. Becauſe of their non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to ſuch edicts of the Empire, as were contrary to the Law of God. 2 Becauſe they talked ſo much of the Kingdom of Chriſt, that in matters of Conference and Worſhip they acknowledged no Soveraignty nor Laws but his. <hi>Trajan</hi>'s Perſecution did ariſe upon <hi>Euariſtus</hi>'s exerciſing of Diſcipline in the Churches, without dependance upon the civil Power. The Emperor <hi>Domitian</hi> did diligently ſearch for all that were any kin to Chriſt according to the Fleſh, leaſt happily ſome of them might lay claim to his Crown; that the primitive Chriſtians were Enemies
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59023:22"/>to Magiſtrates and civil Government was a notorious falſeſhood both their Principles and Practices do abundantly teſtifie, for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times when there were many hundreds of them Burnt in Churches, and thouſands of them that were Soldiers in Arms, able enough to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves, deſtroyed, they chuſed to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, rather than ſinfully to make reſiſtance. 2. They were moſt abominably ſlandered by Magicians, Idolatrous Prieſts, <hi>Jews,</hi> and other Apoſtate Chriſtians, as guilty of the moſt horrid ſins that could be named, at their Meetings; to wit, Inceſt, Adultrey, Drunkenneſs, Inhumanity— 3. Whatever Plagues were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon Perſecutors, the blame of all was caſt upon the Chriſtians, as if they had been the only cauſe thereof; whereas indeed it was their own Sin of Perſecuting God's Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and contempt of the Goſpel, that occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned all their judgments. 4. That they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for Righteouſneſs, may appear from the Laws which were made againſt them; to wit theſe. 1. That all their Bibles ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up and deſtroyed. 2. That they ſhould not meet together for Religious exerciſes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it were Men apart, and Women apart, and ſo Women were to teach Women, contrary to Chriſts Law. 3. That no Miniſters ſhould meet together in any Synod, or otherwiſe; and that wherever they were apprehended they ſhould be carried away to Priſon. The Laws made by <hi>Julian</hi> for the extirpation of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity were theſe. 1. That no Children of Chriſtians ſhould be trained up in Schools, that ſo being ignorant, they might be incapacitated to plead for the Chriſtian Religion 2. That
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59023:23"/>none ſhould be beneficed with any place, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil or military, but they that would Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to Idols. 3. That no Miniſters ſhould have any maintenance. 4. Meerly in ſpite to the Chriſtians, he enacted a toleration to all ſorts of Religion; whence the <hi>Jews</hi> were encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to lay the Foundation of the Temple, that abomination of deſolation, againſt which God did ſo miraculouſly appear from Heaven above, and Earthquakes beneath, that there was not one Stone left upon another, according to what was propheſied by Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God was good to them in this reſpect, That during their Perſecuted Eſtate, he furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with Miniſters, and others ſingularly qualified for the Service and Sufferings of that Day, as may appear, 1. By comparing <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.1, 3, 5, 7. with 4.7. By the Beaſts which cried, Come and ſee, at the opening of the Seals, the Miniſters of Chriſt are ſignified, the firſt was like a Lion, <hi>i. e.</hi> they did deliver their Maſters Meſſage, and do his Work, with an undaunted Lion like Courage and Boldneſs. The ſecond was like a Calf, <hi>i. e.</hi> they were fitted with a Spirit of Patience, and Meekneſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly to undergo the Yoak of hard Labour and ſore Preſſures: The Third had the Face of a Man, <hi>i. e.</hi> they were furniſhed with a great meaſure of Heavenly Wiſdom and Prudence in all their adminiſtrations. The fourth like a flying Eagle, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſome of them did ſoare aloft in ſearching into, and diſcovering of the great Myſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven; they were very Heavenly-minded, and inſiſted much on ſuch things as might make the Chriſtians Dead to all things here below, ſuch a one was <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carpus,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:59023:23"/>who thus anſwered the Proconſul preſſing him to deny Chriſt: Theſe Eighty Six Years I have ſerved a good Maſter, and why ſhould I now deny him? At another time thus, I do even long for the Teeth of the devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Beaſts; they'll only grind us in a Mill, that we may be Wheat fit for our Maſters Table. And <hi>Ignatius</hi> thus, I covet nothing that can be ſeen with Bodily Eyes, ſo that I may but enjoy Jeſus Chriſt. Let the Fire, the Croſs, the Beaſts, the breaking of Bones, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſion of Members, bruiſing of the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the torments of the Devil ſeize upon me, provided I may be partaker of Chriſt. 2. The evidence of this may be evinced, if we conſider, how that through their means the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel did ſo triumphantly conquer and captivate the Hearts and Affections of ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds and thouſands to the obedience of Chriſt, that of <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.2. was applicable to their times. <hi>I ſaw, and behold a white Horſe, and he that ſat on him had a Bow, and a Crown was given unto him, and he went forth conquering and to conquer:</hi> The Goſpel was then ſpread abroad into many ſeveral Nations: There was almoſt no place where the Chriſtian Religion was not profeſt. <hi>Plinius</hi> reports, That the number of Chriſtians did ſo encreaſe, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of Perſecution, that few or none did frequent the Idols Temples and Sacrifices. <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> ſaid, all the other Monarchies have their Bounds and Limits, only Chriſt's Dominion was ſpread over all, and had no Bounds, whence he proved, That Chriſt could be no other but the Son of God: And as the ſame Author relates, If they had all forſaken the Towns of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59023:24"/>they had left them almoſt deſolate. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine fundata eſt eccleſia, Sanguine crevit.</hi> 3. The greatneſs of the Mercy did appear in this, That the Lord did raiſe up ſome of very great eminency, to plead their Cauſe againſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of all ſorts. 1. <hi>Quadratus, Ariſtides, Apollonius, Melito, Aſianus, Juſtin Martyr</hi> and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> did learnedly plead againſt Perſecutors and Preſented their Apologeticks to the Emperors. 2. <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Celſus</hi> did manage their cauſe againſt the Heathens. 3. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> in his Book called, <hi>Dialogus cum Tryphone.</hi> 4. <hi>Tertullian</hi> both againſt <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles.</hi> 5. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> againſt Hereticks 4. As they ſtrenuouſly contended for the truth againſt all Enemies, ſo they laboured mightily to keep the Churches at peace among themſelves, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> who kept the <hi>Weſtern</hi> and <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches in concord, notwithſtanding of their difference about keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Eaſter;</hi> the one pleading it ſhould be kept on the Sabbath, the other on the ſame Day that the <hi>Jews</hi> of old did obſerve; let it fall to be the Sabbath, or ay other Day of the Week, in this Pacificatory Work they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed much, and were very ſucceſsful, till <hi>Victor</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> took upon him to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate them of the <hi>Eaſt, Anno</hi> 200 5. They were ſuch as did with all ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs call aloud upon the Churches to conſider the things that were of greateſt concernment to them in that Eſtate. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. At the opening of every Seal, they called thus, Come and ſee. 1. That this was nothing but what was Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of before. 2. Come and ſee, <hi>i. e.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59023:24"/>that theſe things do not befall you by chance or Fortune, but take ſpecial notice of the Hand of God in all theſe providential Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences. 3. Come and ſee that Perſecutors are limited, they cannot go beyond their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion no further than Providence permits: A Horſe and a Rider is the Type of every one of the four firſt Seals, to ſignifie that the reins of Perſecutors are not upon their own Necks, but were wiſely ordered and guided by the Hand of a skillkful Rider. 4. Come and ſee your own ſins as the procuring cauſe of all theſe Perſecutions and Puniſhments, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon you. <hi>Cyprian Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 4. <hi>Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid patimur, peccata noſtra meruere dum viam domini non tenemus, nee data nobis ad ſalutem caeleſtia mandata ſervamus, fecit dominus noſter voluntatem patris, at nos non facimus domini voluntatem patrimonio &amp; lucro ſtudentes, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biam ſectantes, aemulationi ac diſſentioni vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi> There were theſe particular ſins which he acknowledged to be amongſt them. 1. In general they did not walk ſo cloſe with God as they ſhould have done, nor did they ſtudy exactneſs in keeping the Commands of God, according to the pattern of Chriſt. 2. They did with two much eagerneſs purſue after the World. 3. They were Proud. 4. There were Emulations, Diſſenſions, Envyings and Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions amongſt them. 5. They were not ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted and faithfull in their dealings, as they ſhould have been. <hi>Simplicitatis &amp; fidei negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentis.</hi> 6. They denied themſelves of the World in Words only, but not in Deeds; <hi>ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo verbis ſolis &amp; non factis, renunciantes.</hi> 7. Every one ſought to pleaſe himſelf, diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59023:25"/>others. <hi>Unuſquiſque ſibi placentes &amp; aliis non placentes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Come and ſee the ends of God in all this 1. It is to declare his Holineſs and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; he cannot away with Sin in any, how near or dear ſo ever to him. 2. To humble them for their Sins. 3. To exerciſe their Graces. 4. To diſcover Hypocrites. 5. That the Truths of the Goſpel might be ſufficiently confirmed and commended to after Ages, and ſucceeding Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations: After the Martyrdom of ſo many, there needs no new Miracles, to make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Goſpel. 6. That they might be Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns to us in point of Suffering, demeaning our ſelves as they did.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Come and ſee the ends of God in delaying ſo long to give them deliverance. 1. Becauſe Wicked Men had not yet filled up the meaſure of their Sins. 2. He had a mind to honour ſome more of his Servants with the Crown of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.10. <hi>And it was ſaid unto them that they ſhould reſt for a little ſeaſon until their fellow ſervants alſo and brethren that ſhould be killed as they were, ſhould be fulfilled.</hi> When the ſcrowl of them that God had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out for Sufferings, was made up, then they might expect Deliverance: Hiſtories do relate, that in theſe purer primitive times, before the Apoſtacy of <hi>Rome,</hi> all their Miniſters were Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, till <hi>Sylveſter</hi> the firſt, in <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s days.</p>
            <p n="4">4. God was very good to his People in thoſe days, in giving them now and then ſome breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time and reſpite from the heat of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as after <hi>Domitian</hi>'s Death, they were not troubled for one whole year's time; under <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:59023:25"/>and <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> they were free from Perſecution; after <hi>Decius</hi> they had Peace for forty years together: It's very obſervable, That their Sufferings were little or nothing at all under ſome that were otherwiſe moſt notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Wicked; and they ſuffer'd greatly from ſome that were otherwiſe morally good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, to wit, <hi>Hadrian,</hi> that was called <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaurator Orbis,</hi> and <hi>Trajan,</hi> call'd <hi>Princeps Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus;</hi> inſomuch, that it afterwards became Proverbial, in Congratulating new Emperors with this Salutation, <hi>Foelicior Auguſto, melior Trajano;</hi> ſo alſo under <hi>Antoninus Pius,</hi> and <hi>Severus:</hi> Morality without Grace is ſometimes a greater Enemy to the Goſpel and Kingdom of Chriſt, than open Atheiſm and Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. However, let the Perſons and Inſtruments, under whom they had reſpite, be what they will, all was ſtill to be attributed to the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, who did accompliſh and bring it to paſs, by ſuch wonderful means; ſome where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are theſe. 1. <hi>Antoninus Pius</hi> was taken off from Perſecuting them by that extraordinary act of Providence, in hearing the Prayers of a Legion of Soldiers that were <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his whole Army, in a great ſtrait for Rain, were abundantly refreſhed, and his Enemies mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly defeated; God from Heaven fighting with Thunder and Lightning againſt them, for which that Legion was called, <hi>Legio ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatrix,</hi> the Thundring Legion: This wrought ſo upon the Emperor, that preſently he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhould neither be ſought for, nor puniſhed if preſented, but that their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers ſhould be puniſhed; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>my own ſafety, and the ſafety of my Empire de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59023:26"/>upon their Prayers.</hi> 2. <hi>Aurelianus</hi> having iſſued forth an Edict againſt the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> was ſo terrified with Thunder that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called it. 3. <hi>Alexander Severus</hi> was perſwaded by his Mother <hi>Mammea</hi> to ſhew them favour; ſhe hearing of the Learning of <hi>Origin</hi> ſent for him, and was inſtructed by him. 4. <hi>Hadrian</hi>'s Perſecution was ſomething mitigated by the Apologies which were preſented to him by <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtides</hi> and <hi>Quadratus.</hi> 5. <hi>Antoninus Pius</hi> was made to relent by <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>'s Apologe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. 6. Under <hi>Trajan</hi> the Perſecution was ſtaid by <hi>Plinius Secundus,</hi> who writ to the Emperor concerning their Innocence, That they were not Guilty of the Crimes charged upon them, in regard the Law of their God was very ſtrict againſt ſuch Sins; and that they uſed to meet before Day to Sing Pſalms, and to Worſhip one call'd <hi>JESUS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. God's goodneſs to them was in reſpect of the remarkable Judgments, which he brought upon moſt, if not all of their greateſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors: I'll give you a Summary Survey of the Tragical ends of all of them throughout the Ten Perſecutions. The Firſt was under <hi>Nero, Anno</hi> 67. Who being hated of Men, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued by the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> killed himſelf. Second under <hi>Domitian, Anno</hi> 90. His wife and Friends finding a Roll of the Names of Chriſtians, which he had marked out for ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and their own amongſt the reſt, they killed him. Third under <hi>Trajan, Anno.</hi> 100. who was all his Life time vexed with great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and commotions, and at laſt cut off by a ſtrange Diſeaſe. Fourth under <hi>Hadrian</hi> and <hi>Antoninus Pius, Anno</hi> 126. <hi>Hadrian</hi> Died in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59023:26"/>great horrour of Conſcience; it was he that cryed out, <hi>O animula, vagula, blandula — Pius</hi> Died of a Fever in three Days after he Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Fifth under <hi>Antoninus Philoſophus</hi> and <hi>Verus,</hi> I find nothing recorded of their Death, but <hi>Antoninus</hi> knew much trouble in his Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, from the <hi>Germans, Samaritans, Avidius, Caſſius</hi> and others. Sixth, under <hi>Severus, Anno</hi> 208. He was ſlain at <hi>York,</hi> by the <hi>Northern</hi> Men and <hi>Scots,</hi> and in his time a certain Judge, that pronounced Sentence againſt <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petus,</hi> a holy Martyr, fell from the Bench, and Died ſuddenly. Seventh, under <hi>Maximinus Anno,</hi> 236. He was killed by his own Son, and Soldiers in his Tent at the Seige of <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leia.</hi> Eighth under <hi>Decius, Anno</hi> 251. Being overcome by the <hi>Scythians</hi> or <hi>Gothes,</hi> he threw himſelf into a Pit, where he ended his Life, and his Body could never be found. Ninth, under <hi>Gallus</hi> and <hi>Voluſianus, Anno</hi> 258. A ſad Peſtilence in his time; was ſlain by <hi>Aemilianus,</hi> one of his own Captains, together with his Son. <hi>Valerianus</hi> being overcome by the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, Sopor</hi> trod upon him while he took Horſe. The laſt was under <hi>Diocleſian</hi> and <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian, Anno</hi> 300. Both of them in one Day diveſted themſelves of the imperial dignity; and chuſed to live in Dens and Caves: <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian</hi> afterwards Poiſoned himſelf, rather than he would ſee <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> and <hi>Maximinianus</hi> hanged himſelf.</p>
            <p n="6">6. God was good in giving them a glorious deliverance from this their perſecuted State, and that by the Hands of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> where theſe paſſages of Providence are remarkable. 1. He had a kind of immediate Call from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59023:27"/>both to embrace the Chriſtian Religion, as alſo to go againſt that Perſecuting Tyrant <hi>Maxentius;</hi> witneſs the voice which he heard,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in Chriſt thou ſhalt overcome: <hi>Euſebius</hi> that lived in his time, tells us, That he heard himſelf relate this, confirming it with an Oath. 2. God preſerved him for this Service from the treacherous Deſign of his Father in Law <hi>Maximinianus,</hi> his Wife having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered it to him. 3. <hi>Maxentius</hi> had made a device to drown him and his Men, when he paſſed over a Bridge, by which <hi>Maxentius</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was afterward drowned, and he eſcaped, for which the Chriſtians ſung, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.16. And 7.15. 4. Having giving himſelf to Faſting and Prayer, he obtained Victory over <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus</hi> and <hi>Licinius;</hi> and though <hi>Licinius</hi> had once greatly reproached Chriſt and Chriſtianity yet being brought to condign Puniſhment, he was made to confeſs that great was the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians God, and great was <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s God.</p>
            <p>Let's make ſome Application of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in theſe few Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This calls upon us highly to eſteem of the glorious Truths of Chriſt, in regard they have been Sealed and Witneſſed to with the Blood of ſo many Millions of Martyrs. O how wonderful are the Ways of God that would take ſuch a Courſe to commend the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of the Son of God to us, who knows, but they of that Age ſuffered, that we and others might at leaſt in a great meaſure be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though they excuſed us ſo far that the Church is never like to be in a Perſecuted State for Three hundred Years together, yet there
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59023:27"/>is no Age in which this, or t'other particular Perſon can promiſe an exemption from Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution to himſelf; and therefore it ſounds an Alarm to us in the times of our greateſt Peace and Proſperity, to prepare for Perſecution: Lay in a ſtock of Suffering Graces before, that ſo it may never ſurprize you unawares, but, come when it will, you may be ready for it. Take ſpecial notice of theſe three things. 1. Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution has been in all Ages, an inſeparable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant of the plain and faithful Preaching of the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.34, 35. 2. It was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver better with the Church and People of God than in times of Perſecution; there was never a more glorious Luſtre and Beauty upon Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; Miniſters never more Lively and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual; the Converſation of Chriſtians never more in Heaven; and the number of Converts never more encreaſed. 3. Be confirmed in this, That the ſpeciality of God's Love in Chriſt to his People, may very well ſtand with their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a Perſecuted Condition; ſo that it may be always ſaid, <hi>Truly God is good to Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In all your Sufferings ſet the Martyrs of thoſe times before you as Patterns for imitation. 1. As I would not have you decline Sufferings for the Goſpel and Righteouſneſs ſake, when indeed called of God thereunto, ſo be careful not to ſuffer as Buſie bodies, or Evil-doers: Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom for Chriſt was accounted ſo honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble amongſt them, that the Names of all that were Martyrs indeed, were regiſter'd, and kept upon Record; and ſuch as did Suffer, either not for Truth, or without a Call, out of an itching appetite for Honour, were not Enroll'd. 2. In all your Sufferings own Magiſtracy, and honour
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59023:28"/>the Authority of Magiſtrates; I am ſure this was the Doctrine and Practice of Chriſt, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and the purer primitive Churches. 3. Shew all Meekneſs towards your Perſecutors, that they may be convinced, it is not through a peeviſh humourſomneſs or Pride, but really for Conſcience ſake, becauſe you dare not ſin againſt God, that you do and ſuffer what you do; condeſcend to them in all things civil, unleſs they impoſe upon your Conſciences, ſomething contrary to God's Word. 4. Shew Love to the Souls of thoſe that hate you with a moſt cruel hatred, in praying ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, heartily, and conſtantly for them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. end. 5. Do not uſe any ſinful or unlawful means to deliver your ſelf from ſufferings, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25, 26. 6. As I would have none to venture upon ſufferings in their own Strength a Fleſhly confidence will fail you in an Hour of Temptation, ſo let not the ſenſe of thy own weakneſs cauſe diſcouragement and a deſpondence of Spirit, but rather act depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon this good God, that when ever he gives the Call, he will proportion thy Strength in ſome meaſure to thy Sufferings, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. 7. Theſe primitive Martyrs were not only patient, but of a chearful Spirit in all their Sufferings, they Sung Pſalms to one Jeſus. Let this be the Goſpel-Frame of Spirit you are of, <hi>in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing give thanks, for this is the will of God your Heavenly Father,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.18. 8. Be much in Prayer, in the exerciſe of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and of Faith, in applying particular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to your own Souls, and in realizing the Glorious things of Eternity. 9. In all your Sufferings be public Spirited. <hi>i. e.</hi> Let Gods
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59023:28"/>Glory, the honour of the Goſpel, the Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Churches and Chriſtians, and thy own Souls Advantage be aimed at: Do not think how thou mayeſt get Honour and a Name to thy ſelf, but rather (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou doſt do or ſuffer, let all be for the Glory of God. 10. Think it not enough to begin well, but reſolve in the Lord's Strength to continue faithful to the Death, and thou ſhalt be ſure of the Crown of Life.</p>
            <p n="7">7. God was good to his People from <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi>'s time, and the firſt beginning of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts Riſe, to his full height, and to put the two laſt in one, he has been good to them ever ſince he began to decay, and will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his Goodneſs to them more and more, to the end of the World: And here it will be neceſſary for your better underſtanding of this Subject, to premiſe a few things. 1. No ſooner was the Church delivered from a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted State, but immediately upon the back of that, a new Storm did ariſe. 2. The Churches Tryals now, are of a different Nature from what they were formerly, as then they Suffered from profeſſed Pagans, ſo now they are exerciſed with Spiritual Judgments, they were peſtered with Hereſies and Errors from within, and ſuch as by Profeſſion were Chriſtians. 3. This is not ſo to be underſtood, as if they ſhall not now ſuffer Perſecution, but the Denomination of the Churches State, is from that which is Chief and Principal of the two Evils, Hereſies were the greateſt. 4. The Inſtruments by whom they ſuffered, were Antichriſt and his Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. 5. In treating of theſe things, I ſhall take it for granted, that the Churches ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59023:29"/>in this Age, is contained under the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, 8. and 9. Chap. of the <hi>Revel.</hi> 6. I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the 7th Chap. of the <hi>Revel.</hi> to be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a preparative to the ſounding of the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, and intervenes between the opening of the 6th and 7th Seals, as alſo that the 10th Chap. and beginning of the 11th is no new Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy diſtinct from the Propheſy of the Trumpets, but only intervenes between the 6th and 7th. 7. I muſt ſpeak particularly and more largely than I intended of the evils of this Age, that ſo the Goodneſs of God in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving them from the ſame, may appear to be the greater, and ſo for methods ſake, I ſhall ſummarily give you the ſubſtance of the 7th, 8th, 9th, 10th, 11th, Chap. of the <hi>Revel.</hi> as they lie in order.</p>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Revelations</hi> Chap. Seven.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Take notice, that the Nature of the Evil to enſue is hinted at <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2. There were <hi>Four Angels ſtanding on the four Corners of the Earth, holding the four Winds, that they ſhould not blow upon the Earth, nor on the Sea, nor on the Trees.</hi> This was the Judgment that was to come upon earthy, unſtable and ſelf-conceited Profeſſors of the viſible Church, even a ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of the influences of the North and South-Wind of the Spirit, throughout all the Corners of the Earth. 2. It is obſervable that this, nor any other kind of evil can befal Creatures by chance, but by the Hand of an over-Ruling Divine providence. Four Angels are Empowered and Commiſſioned from above, before the thing be put in Execution. 3. From verſe 2.3. Obſerve, Such is God's Goodneſs,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59023:29"/>and Chriſt's tender Care towards his poor People, that he ſuffers not theſe Commiſſioned Executioners of Divine Juſtice, to go on haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with their Work, till they were ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently prepared and guarded againſt it. 4. The Great Lord Chancellor, the Keeper of the Great Seal of Heaven, is pleaſed to ſet his own Mark upon his choſen Ones, whereby they may be enſafed, and ſecured againſt this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Evil: Hurt not — till we have Sealed the Servants of our God in their Foreheads. He gives them that excellent Unction 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. and anointing of the Spirit, that though Antichriſtian Calamities may reach their Bodies, yet they ſhall never be able to do their Souls any conſiderable hurt. 5. herein is the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God yet further, that during Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts Rage, the Sealed Ones are exactly Numbred to a Man, in the Court-Rolls of Heaven One Hundred Forty Four Thouſand out of all the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael, i. e.</hi> as the Twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were but few in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of other Nations, and the Elect of God among themſelves, were but few in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of thoſe that were called <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> ſo the Number of thoſe that are preſerved from Antichriſtian Pollutiones ſhall be few in reſpect of a world of carnal Profeſſors, that ſhall wonder after the Beaſt. 6. From verſe 9. to the end, you have an excellent prophetical hint of their deliverance from Antichriſtianiſm, and then their Condition ſhall be glorious compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, <hi>i. e.</hi> in reſpect of her Wilderneſs conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and propheſying in Sackcloath; then ſhall there be a multitude which no Man can Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, of all Nations, and they ſhall ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59023:30"/>the Throne, and before the Lamb. Tho' it was hardly viſible, whether there was a Church or no formerly, yet now they ſhall openly ſhew themſelves, Cloathed with white Robes, to ſhew that they have ſhaken off Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, with its Doctrine of Merits, Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, Penances and Satisfactions, and ſeek Juſtification only by Faith in Chriſt, and his Righteouſneſs; having Palms in their Hands, as a ſign of Victory over the Beaſt, over his Mark, his Image, and the Number of his Name; and they cried with a loud Voice, Salvation of our God, which ſitteth upon the Throne, and to the Lamb, and the Angels alſo fell on their Faces before the Throne, and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped God, ſaying, Amen. Bleſſing, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Wiſdom, and Thankſgiving and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Power, and Might, be unto our God, for ever and ever, Amen. The State of the Church, ſhall now be a kind of Heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, in compariſon of what it was du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Antichriſts Reign, and her Glory ſhall ſtill encreaſe from one Degree to another, till ſhe be fully poſſeſſed of Heaven it ſelf, where their ſhall be a total exemption from all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and an abundant affluence of all good, truly God is good to <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>Chapter Eighth.</head>
               <p>This Eighth Chapter does under the Firſt four Trumpets, contain as I humbly conceive the Churches Sufferings for the next Three Hundred Years after <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> where ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. 1. Upon opening the Seventh Seal, there was ſilence in Heaven for half an hour, <hi>i. e.</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:59023:30"/>for ſome ſhort time the Church had ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite from outward Commotions and Troubles; and this is to be reckon'd among the Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of God's goodneſs to them; or it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a holy attention in Heaven's Inhabitants, the Chriſtians, to what God ſhall be pleas'd to ſpeak to them by this Seal, that brings forth Seven ſeveral Trumps, and each of them a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Judgment; it put them in a kind of amaze to conſider, That no ſooner they were deliver'd from <hi>Paganiſh</hi> Perſecutions, which laſted for Three hundred Years, but immediately there's a new Cloud a gathering.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To the Seven Angels, which ſtood before God, were given Seven Trumpets, <hi>v.</hi> 2. to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate God's goodneſs in this, That he did ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly denounce Wrath and Judgment againſt Carnal Chriſtians, that began to corrupt their Ways, and thereby did call aloud upon them to Repent; Trumpets are for an Alarm to War, and they give a diſtinct ſound, that every one may know their Duty: So good is God, that he is not willing that any ſhould Periſh, but all ſhould come to the knowledge of the Truth, Repent and be Saved.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Even in thoſe Days God had a Praying People, whoſe Perſons and Prayers found ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, through the Interceſſion of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Verſe</hi> 3, 4. <hi>Another Angel came, and ſtood at the Altar, having a golden cenſer, and there was given unto him much incenſe, that he ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it with the prayers of the Saints, upon the golden Altar which was before the throne; and the ſmoak of the incenſe, which came with the prayers of the Saints, aſcended up before God out of the Angel's hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:59023:31"/>
               <p n="4">4. The very ſame Angel of the Covenant, Chriſt himſelf, takes ſome Fire from off the Altar, and caſts it into the Earth: <hi>And then there were voices, and thundrings, and lightnings, and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes,</hi> v. 5. It's he that perfumes the Saints Prayers, that plagues and puniſhes the world of Apoſtate Profeſſors with ſpiritual Judgments; All Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is committed of the Father to the Son, and therefore the Sealed ones may be ſecure; they need not be afraid of what ſhall fall out. O the goodneſs of God in this thing: And now! come to the Trumpets themſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When the firſt Angel ſounded, there followed hail and fire mingled with blood, and they were caſt upon the earth, and the third part of the trees were burnt up, and all green graſs was burnt up,</hi> verſ. 7. This may be fitly applied to Arrianiſm, the firſt ſpiritual Plague wherewith the Church was peſtered even in <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s time; It brought Hail with it, which is a cold and nipping thing, deſtructive, eſpecially to Trees and Graſs. Many Trees, <hi>i. e.</hi> Eminent Ones, became cold in matters of Worſhip, and in their Love one to another: And all Graſs was burnt up, <hi>i. e.</hi> The generality of common Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors throughout the World were much Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized into Arrianiſm: There was Fire mingled with Blood, <hi>i. e.</hi> It produced a moſt bloody Perſecution of all that were Aſſerters of the Divinity of Chriſt, and his being Co equal, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſential and Co-eternal with the Father.</p>
               <p>God's goodneſs under this Trumpet was in theſe two, 1. There was but a third part of the Trees burnt up, <hi>i. e.</hi> There were ſeveral Perſons of great Note, both Magiſtrates and Miniſters, who did, even in thoſe days, faithfully witneſs
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59023:31"/>to the Truth; of Emperors, <hi>Conſtantine, Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinian, Gratian, Theodoſius;</hi> of Miniſters, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander, Hoſius, Foelix Secundus,</hi> &amp;c. 2. Tho' Fundamental Truths were much ſtruck at, yet the Lord cauſed the Earth to help the Woman, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.16. <hi>i. e.</hi> Tho' their Synods and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils did begin to grow very earthly, carnal, and corrupt, yet God made uſe of them for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fervation of Fundamental Controverted Truths, in there Purity and Incorruption. In the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Nice,</hi> call'd by <hi>Conſtantine, Anno</hi> 330. Arrianiſm was abundantly confuted; in that of <hi>Conſtantinople, Anno</hi> 380. under <hi>Gratian</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius. Macedonius,</hi> and his Followers, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe they denyed the Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Holy Ghoſt, were confuted: The Third great Council at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> under <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> II. <hi>Anno</hi> 431. did condemn <hi>Neſtorius</hi>'s hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Chriſt had two Perſons: The Fourth at <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> under <hi>Martianus, An.</hi> 451. condemned the Eutychians confounding the Natures of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Upon the ſounding of the Second Trumpet <hi>There was as it were, a mountain burning with fire caſt into the Sea; and the third part of the Sea became blood; and the third part of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which were in the Sea, and had life, died; and the third part of the Ships were deſtroyed,</hi> i.e. Now began hot conteſts between Church-men for Precedency; and this did quickly corrupt the Ordinances themſelves, the Seas and Ships, by which, Chriſtians, as ſuch, do maintain a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Trade and Commerce with God and one with another: Contentions among Church-men were a fair Foundation, laid by the Dragon, for the intended and deſigned Superſtructure of Antichriſtianiſm; and they were kindled, 1. By
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59023:32"/>their own Pride and Ambition. 2. By reaſon of the great Benefices beſtowed upon them by <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> witneſs that Voice then heard, <hi>Hodie venenum effuſum eſt in eccleſiam,</hi> this day Poiſon is poured out on the Church: It might then be ſaid, <hi>Religio peperit divitias, &amp; filia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voravit matrem.</hi> 3. They had the favour of the Emperors, and great Men. 4. Becauſe their Miniſtry was in the Imperial Seat, they claim'd more than ordinary Privileges. 5. Some good Men, being much wrong'd and injur'd, by the unjuſt Sentences and Church-Cenſures, iſſued forth againſt them in the Eaſtern Councils, did addreſs themſelves to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as being then moſt pure, that they would interpoſe for ſome Remedy and Redreſs, which was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſo much abuſed, That the See of <hi>Rome</hi> claim'd it as a privilege, That all Appeals ſhould be made to them; as may appear in the caſe of <hi>Appiarius,</hi> at a Council of <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> This being withſtood by the Eaſtern Churches, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned many hot Debates; and now it was that they had Wooden Biſhops, and Golden Chalices; whereas, in the days of Perſecution, they had Golden Biſhops, but Wooden Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lices.</p>
               <p>The goodneſs of God, under this Trumpet, was, in ſuffering only a third part of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to be corrupted; he preſerves ſtill ſome, both Profeſſors and Ordinances, from Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Pollutions.</p>
               <p>Upon the ſounding of the Third Angel, <hi>There fell a great Star from heaven, burning as it were a lamp, and it fell upon the third part of the Rivers, and upon the fountains of waters; and the name of the Star is called Wormwood; and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59023:32"/>the third part o the waters became Wormwood, and many men died of the waters, becauſe they were made bitter,</hi> i. e. Now the Apoſtacy grows higher, whereas before Trees, and Graſs, and Seas, now Rivers and Fountains are Corrupted, <hi>i. e.</hi> The very Scriptures, and ſome of the choiceſt Streams thereof, which convey ſpiritual Light and Life to Souls, were much perverted, the preceding Trumpers did ſtrike at Chriſt in his Perſon and Natures, this at his Offices; now comes in the Doctrine of Merit, Popiſh Pennances, Indulgences, Mediators, Invocation of Saints. This is fitly applicable to <hi>Pelagius,</hi> who lived in the days of <hi>Honorius</hi> and <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> An. 405, or 415, He corrupted the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace it ſelf; that River, the Streams whereof make glad the People of God: He was a great Star, that did burn as it were a Lamp; he was a Man of great Parts and ſeemingly Godly; but it was only the flouriſhes of natural and acquired Accompliſhments, not ſaving Grace wherewith he did ſhine.</p>
               <p>God's goodneſs here was in this, that he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd only a third part of the Waters to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitter'd, tho' <hi>Pelaganiſm</hi> did exceedingly ſpread through <hi>Italy, France,</hi> and <hi>Britain,</hi> yet the Lord had ſtill ſome eminent Lights in the Church, that ſet themſelves againſt it; to wit, <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, Jerome, Proſper, Optatus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Upon the ſounding of the Fourth Angel, <hi>The third part of the Sun was darkned, and the third part of the Moon, and the third part of the Stars, and the day ſhone not for a third part of it, and the night likewiſe,</hi> i. e. This degree of Apoſtacy is ſo much higher than the former, as the Sun Moon, and Stars, are higher than the Earth,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59023:33"/>Seas, Fountains, and Rivers; Now Darkneſs does in a great meaſure overſpread the whole Face of the viſible Church; former Evils did ariſe from Pride and Ambition, more than Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, but now both go together: This is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to the Sixth Century, wherein lights of all ſorts came to be Darkned and Obſcured, there was a general decay of Simplicity and Purity in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government; a thick Veil upon Scriptures, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, Ordinances, People, and All; now the Goſpel was much eclypſed with Humane Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, Cerem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nies, and Superſtitions; now we read of building of Abbies and Monaſtries, of Kings and Queens deſerting a Married ſtare to go a Pilgrimage, meerly out of a blind De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, multiplying of holy Days; and many other Superſtitious Fopperies. God's goodneſs alſo here is obvious from the Text; a third part of the Sun only was darkned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as alſo from the laſt verſe, which is only a Tranſition to what follows, intimating, that tho' theſe four Woes that are paſt be great, yet there are three greater to come, tho' the Churches affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, during this Century, were very ſad, yet not comparable to what others, eſpecially thoſe of the ſucceeding Age, encountred with.</p>
               <p>A few words of Application. 1. From all this we may learn, That one of the greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns that ever the Devil had againſt the Church was to corrupt Truths, Ordinances, and Worſhip. Let us therefore Counter-work him in ſtudying and endeavouring nothing more, than the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Purity of the Goſpel both in Doctrine and Worſhip. 2. So hard a matter it is for Profeſſors and Preachers to have their Garments
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59023:33"/>kept clean from ſuch pollution, that the Seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God by Jeſus Chriſt are the only preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative againſt the ſame: It is not Morality, Learning, Policy, or great Parts, without ſaving Grace, that will do. All you that are in any meaſure chaſt Virgins, acknowledge the Lord Keeper of the Great Seal of Heaven for this rich Mercy. 3. As I obſerved before, that the Church never knew a more thriving time than under Perſecution; ſo it never fared worſe with them, than in a time of temporal and ſecular Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: Let us therefore, when God calls to it, be content with Perſecution, as well as Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. 4. From what has been ſaid, it's clear as the Sun, That the great Antichriſt had his firſt Riſe and Origination out of the Aſhes of the Pride and Covetouſneſs of the carnal Clergy; and where-ever theſe are found in this Day, I dare be bold to ſay, It is a piece of Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſm, mark'd out for Deſtruction, by the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judge of all the World. 5. Much of God's goodneſs is in this, That all theſe Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets are not ſounded together, but one after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and he begins to puniſh with leſſer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he proceed to greater Judgments. O ſtand in awe and ſin not; take warning by one Rod, otherwiſe thou ſhalt know that he has more Rods than one. 6. We ſee Antichriſt's Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Advancement was by degrees, and ſo ſhall alſo his Ruine, therefore we had need of Patience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. <hi>Ninth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This Chapter contains two Trumpets more; the 5th from the beginning to <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. and 6th to the end. The 5th holds forth the Myſtery
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59023:34"/>of Iniquity as higher than ever, ſo that things cannot be in a more Corrupted State than now, the method I ſhall obſerve ſhall be as briefly as may be to open the Words as they lie in order.</p>
               <p>Upon the founding of the firſt Angel. 1. You have the fall of a Star from Heaven to Earth; this is <hi>Boniface</hi> the Third Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who <hi>Anno</hi> 606 got himſelf to be ſtiled univerſal Biſhop, by the means of <hi>Phocas,</hi> after he had killed his Maſter <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperor. 2. His Commiſſion ſhewed him to be the Dragons Lord Lieutenant. Whereas Originally Miniſters did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven, from Chriſt, Antichriſt receives the Keys of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pit, and derives his Authority from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You have the Execution of his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, no ſooner is he inveſted with this Power, but he improves it; he opened the bottomleſs Pit, now Hell it ſelf is ſet looſe, to do what miſchief it can. Verſe 2.4. The effects that followed upon this opening, are theſe Two, 1. There aroſe a Smoak like the Smoak of a great Furnace, whereby the Sun and Air were Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>i. e.</hi> whereas under the fourth Trumpet on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Third part of the Sun was Darkned; Now there is a total Eclipſe, and a thick Miſt upon the Face of the whole Earth; the petty Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts that preceded, did only Corrupt and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterate ſome Truths and Ordinances: Thus all. His Smoak is as the Smoak of a great Furnace, a complex Body, a Flood and Inundation of all manner of Errors and Hereſies: He calls all that endeavour a Reformation in Doctrine, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Diſcipline, Hereticks and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, but indeed, he is the great Heretick.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59023:34"/>2. Out of this Smoak came out Locuſts. Verſe 3. <hi>i. e.</hi> the Romiſh and Antichriſtian Clergy, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Locuſts. 1. Becauſe there are ſuch nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous ſwarms of them, that were never of Divine Inſtitution. Popes, Cardinals, Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, Metropolitans, Arch-Biſhops, Lord-Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſome do reckon 35 orders of that Hierarchy, to which <hi>Alſted</hi> ſays do belong 225044 Monaſtaries. 2. Becauſe of their hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to Souls, as Locuſts to Trees and Graſs. They are further deſcribed from verſe 4. to the end of this Trumpet, the Spirit of God hereby pointing to us, That this Romiſh Hierarchy is one of the greateſt Pillars of Antichriſts Kingdom; where you may mark theſe properties in them. 1. They have power to String, <hi>i. e.</hi> to torment the Souls and Conſciences of Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Verſe 3, 5, 6. They ſhall ſo put them on the Rack, <hi>That in thoſe days Men ſhall ſeek Death, and ſhall not find it, they ſhall deſire Death, and it ſhall flee away.</hi> They Preach that they muſt believe as the Church believeth, that they muſt perfectly keep the Law of God, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they are Damned — and having thus wounded, the Remedy is worſe than the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe; they put Men upon ſatisfying God's Juſtice at leaſt for ſome ſins, and procuring Peace of Conſcience by their own good Works and Merits, that no Man can be aſſured of his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in this Life, that after Death their Souls go into Purgatory, out of which they are to be redeemed by ſaying ſo many Soul-Maſſes for them, for which they muſt endow the Church with a good part of their Eſtates: This their Stinging was like unto a Scorpion a dangerous kind of Serpent, that goes wayward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59023:35"/>and Stings when it ſeems not to do ſo: Their Power thus to torment, was but for five Months, this is in alluſion to the Locuſts who continue from <hi>April</hi> to <hi>September,</hi> to deſtroy Trees and Graſs. Verſe 5.2. As to their ſhape, they were like unto Horſes prepared unto Battle, <hi>i. e.</hi> they are ſwift, nimble and active, ſtrong and well fed, meer belly-Gods. 3. On their Heads they have Crowns, as it were like unto Gold, <hi>i. e.</hi> they live in ſuch State, Pomp and Grandure, that they are more like Monarchs than Goſpel-Miniſters, though indeed they are neither, for their Crowns are not Gold, but like unto it; they plead that their Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is of Divine Right, their Authority is from Jeſus Chriſt, but all is not Gold that gliſters, pretend what they will, they came out of the bottomleſs Pit. 4. <hi>Their faces were as the faces of Men.</hi> Verſe 7. i. e. They ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves very ſociable and affable, meerly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate into the Affections of others, or, they plead, its reaſon by which they are regulated in all their Adminiſtrations, is it not reaſon that all things ſhould be done decently and in order, that the Church ſhould have a Power in Ceremonies and Matters indifferent to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Practices of People, how can their be any peace without Uniformity? Non confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts can be no other but a company of proud Perſons that affect Novelty and Singularity. 5. <hi>Their hair is like the hair of Women.</hi> Verſe 8. <hi>i. e.</hi> They are Spiritually Effeminate, and with their whoriſh Deckings and Attire, they allure others to commit Spiritual Fornication. 6. <hi>Their teeth are as the teeth of Lions.</hi> Verſe 8, <hi>i. e.</hi> They are very, cruel but cunning, the teeth
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59023:35"/>lie hid; in this they are diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Turks</hi> in the following Trumpet, <hi>Whoſe heads are as lions,</hi> i. e. They openly profeſs their Cruelty. 7. <hi>They had breaſt-plates as it were of iron,</hi> i. e. They arm themſelves ſo, that none can do them hurt, either they get Magſtirates to be on their ſide, or to be privileged with immunities from the jurisdiction of Magiſtrates. 8. <hi>The ſound of their wings is as the ſound of Chariets of many horſes, running to battle,</hi> i. e. Their Church Cenſures, Bulls and Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications is with great noiſe, horror, and dread, by which Emperors and Kings them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have been greatly awed. 9. <hi>They have ſtings in their tails.</hi> Verſe 10. <hi>i. e.</hi> With their flattering Speeches, and plauſible Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences they captivate poor ſimple ones. Laſtly, <hi>They have a King over them, which is the Angel of the bottomleſs Pit, whoſe name in the Hebrew tongue is Abaddon, deſtroyer.</hi> i. e. Though they have many ſeveral orders and degrees amongſt themſelves, yet they are all of them ſubordinate to one ſupream Head the Pope; though ſome may pretend very fair, yet their Offices, Orders and Degrees, came Originally from him that is the Angel of the bottomleſs Pit.</p>
               <p>The goodneſs of God under this trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet is in the 9th, Verſe. Though their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion was very extenſive in having power to hurt all, yet it did not reach the Sealed Ones, and to ſay no more but this, the greater the judgment was, the more did the goodneſs of God appear in ſecuring his hidden Ones from it. And thus of the 5th Trumpet.</p>
               <p>The Scope of the ſixth Trumpet, is to ſhow that Idolatry and Superſtition being now ſo
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59023:36"/>rife amongſt thoſe that were called Chriſtians; the Righteous God was reſolved to raiſe up the <hi>Sarazens</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> as a ſcourge for the ſame, the judgment of this Trumpet not being a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, but a Temporal one. Moſt Expreſſions may be underſtood literally; I will curſorily run over the whole.</p>
               <p>Upon the ſounding of the ſixth Angel, a voice was heard from the 4 Horns of the Golden Altar which is before God, ſaying, <hi>Looſe the four An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels which are bound in the great River Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> which was accordingly done Verſe 14.15. <hi>i. e.</hi> Whereas the forementioned barbarous Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were hereto by God's Providence reſtrained from breaking in upon the Weſtern part of the World, and kept on the other ſide of <hi>Euphrates,</hi> now they are commiſſioned from Jeſus Chriſt to come againſt the Chriſtians for their Idolatry. <hi>The number of the army of the horſemen, were two hundred thouſand thouſand,</hi> i. e. Of all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the World none comparable to the <hi>Turks</hi> for Horſes; they are infinitely numerous, <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>And the riders that ſat on them have breaſt-plates of fire, of jacinct, and of brimſtone, and the heads of the horſes were as the heads of lions,</hi> i. e. they are terrible and cruel, and profeſs themſelves to be ſo; <hi>and out of their mouths iſſued fire and ſmoak, and brimſtone:</hi> Some underſtand hereby their great Guns and Cannons, which Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of War were firſt invented by them, <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>And by the fire, ſmoak, and brimſtone, which iſſued out of their mouths, the third part of men were killed,</hi> ver. 18. The Locuſts work was but to torment and hurt, but theſe do make ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock, kill and deſtroy; <hi>Their power alſo is in their mouth and in their tails, for their tails
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59023:36"/>were like unto ſerpents, and had heads, and with them they do hurt,</hi> ver. 19. <hi>i. e.</hi> As they exerciſe horrid cruelty in killing the Bodies of Men and Women, ſo alſo they vent peſtiferous Doctrine in their Alcoran and Mahometan Religion; the Locuſts had the ſtings of Scorpions in their tails, but <hi>Mahomet</hi> has not only the ſting of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, but alſo the head of a Serpent; does open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear upon his tail, <hi>i. e.</hi> Popery is a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity, but any may eaſily diſcover the <hi>Turks</hi> Alcoran to be nothing elſe but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound of <hi>Judaiſm, Paganiſm,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianiſm:</hi> This to me is a ſtrong Argument, why the <hi>Pope,</hi> not the <hi>Turk,</hi> muſt be the Great Antichriſt. And the reſt of the Men which were not killed by theſe Plagues yet repented not of the Works of their hands that they ſhould not Worſhip Devils and Idols of Gold and Silver and Braſs, Stone and Wood, neither can See, and Hear nor Walk. Verſe 20. <hi>i. e</hi> Notwithſtanding all the judgments wherewith God puniſhed the Papiſts for their Idolatry, yet they repented not, but remained Idolatrous ſtill, neither repented they of their Murthers; they killed the Souls and Bodies of Men as faſt as ever, nor of their Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries, they did bewitch and allure People to their Whoriſh Worſhips ſtill, nor of their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications, Spiritual or Bodily, the Pope is ſaid to have Forty Thouſand Crowns a Year by Stews and Bawdy Houſes, nor of their thefts. Verſe 21. Though moſt of their Church-Lands and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues were Originally got by indirect courſes cozening many poor Creatures, in making them give away their Eſtates, for ſaying ſome Soul-Maſſes, to redeem them out of Purgatory, yet they will not make reſtitution, they accuſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59023:37"/>of Sacrilege, that would but reſume and take back their own, while they themſelves are moſt impiouſly Sacrilegious.</p>
               <p>God's Goodneſs in reference to this Trumpet, is, 1. That in the management of this great Affair, of Commiſſioning the <hi>Turk</hi> againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> lies upon Jeſus Chriſt. O bleſſed be our God that takes ſo great care of Chriſtians. 2. The <hi>Turks</hi> Commiſſion is principally againſt the Weſtern Idolaters on this ſide <hi>Euphrates,</hi> he that ſet bounds to the raging of the Waves of the Sea, has limited him that he can go ſo far and no farther: And hence it is that we in this part of the World have never received any conſiderable hurt by him, nor are ever like to receive hurt hereafter, unleſs we ſhall Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize to open Idolatry. 3. As his Commiſſion is limited both as to Perſons and Places, ſo alſo as to Times; the time of his Rage and Reign ſhall be <hi>for an hour, and a day, and a month, and a year.</hi> ver. 15. <hi>i. e.</hi> It is exactly reckoned and calculated with God to an hour. 4. Tho' God deſtroys and makes havock of a third part of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Dominions by the <hi>Turks,</hi> yet the myſtery of Iniquity is not ſo much as once touched by them; the Diſcovery and Deſtruction thereof he reſerves for ſome others of his dear Servants, which ſhall be done under the next Trumpet. 5. O how good is this God, and what a miracle of Mercy is it, that he will grant ſome time for Repentance, even to Antichriſtian Sinners, that he will ſend Judgments on purpoſe to bring them to Repentance; extraordinary means, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the greatneſs of their Diſeaſes! O the Long-ſuffering and Patience of God, that notwithſtanding of their Impenitency, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>improving
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59023:37"/>of Providences, he does not utterly, in an inſtant, deſtroy them, but delays the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his Juſtice and Wrath, as at this day, and if his Long-ſuffering and Patience be ſo great to his Enemies, what will his goodneſs be to his Friends? Bleſſed be our God that has begun to give Antichriſt ſuch a blow by the <hi>Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> it is to me an infallible aſſuring Evidence, that the Work ſhall go on and proſper till it come to its full period.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>Chapter Tenth.</head>
               <p>This whole Chapter and the beginning of the Eleventh to the 15th <hi>verſe,</hi> I underſtand to be a preparation to the ſounding of the 7th Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and that for the comfort of God's People, who might be apt to droop and deſpond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the event of all thoſe ſad diſpenſations, Antichriſt being brought to a great height under the foregoing Trumpets, and they not knowing what way God would take to turn the Scales.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It's here in a Viſion ſhewed to <hi>John,</hi> that Antichriſt perſiſting impenitent for all that the <hi>Turks</hi> had done, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.21. Chriſt himſelf would now take ſome courſe with him: He is deſcribed as a mighty Angel coming down from Heaven, <hi>Cloathed with a cloud,</hi> as a ſign of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Glory and Majeſty, <hi>having a Rainbow on his head,</hi> by this repreſentation to aſſure them that he would prove a Covenant-keeping God, that Antichriſt ſhall not Lord it over them at the old rate, <hi>his face was as the Sun, and his feet as pillars of fire,</hi> ver. 1. <hi>i. e.</hi> In his bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ruine on Antichriſt he ſhall be very Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, it ſhall be with ſuch clearneſs and perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59023:38"/>of Light, as ſhall be ſufficient to diſpel all the Smoak that aroſe out of the Bottomleſs Pit; and it ſhall be with a Power and Efficacy irreſiſtible. 2. We have ſome intimation of the way Chriſt will take for the accompliſhment of this; <hi>He had an open book in his hand, and he ſet his right foot on the ſea, and his left foot on the earth, and cryed with a loud voice, as when a lyon cryeth, and when he cryed ſeven thunders uttered their voices;</hi> ver. 2, 3, 4. i. e. He will make the plain and powerful preaching of the Goſpel, to have a more free paſſage through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the World than formerly: The Command <hi>John</hi> had to Seal up theſe things, may ſignifie that what is here hinted belongs to ſome other Prophecy in this Book, the clear and full Revelation whereof is to be reſerved till the time of its fulfilling. 3. Becauſe the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Antichriſt, after he had domineered for ſo many hundred Years, ſeems almoſt impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and incredible; therefore Chriſt does, for the confirmation of the Faith of his poor weak Ones, enter into a ſolemn Oath, <hi>By him that liveth for ever, who created the heaven and the things that are therein — that time ſhall be no longer, and that the ſeventh trumpet ſhould finiſh the myſtery of God,</hi> ver. 5, 6, 7. His time of Reigning ſhall be no longer, his Ruine ſhall now certainly begin, and be carryed on till time be no more. 4. The Book in the Angel's hand is given to <hi>John,</hi> who, Eating it, finds it ſweet in his Mouth as honey, but bitter in the Belly, <hi>ver.</hi> 8, 9, 10, 11. Chriſt has not only perfect knowledge of theſe Myſteries himſelf, the Book is open in his hand, but alſo he qualifies ſome of his faithful Goſpel-miniſters, not only to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59023:38"/>preach the Everlaſting Goſpel, but more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to propheſie <hi>Babylon</hi>'s Downfall, which tho' it be a very delightful and pleaſing piece of ſervice in the doing of it, yet afterwards it expoſes them to ſore Perſecutions that prove bitter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. Eleven.</head>
               <p>The former Chapter having Propheſied of <hi>Rome</hi>'s ruine, of the Diſcovery and Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Myſtery of Iniquity and Son of Perdition, and that by the preaching of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Goſpel, a doubt now ariſes concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fulfilling of this, how can there be any Propheſying or Preaching where there is no Church, and if there be no Church, there can be no Prophets? Antichriſt has now poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed himſelf of the Temple of God, and ſo Corrupted all under the foregoing Trumpets, as has been already cleared, that it's hardly viſible whether Chriſt have any Church or Kingdom in the World. This Chap. ſolves this Scruple, and affords ſome grounds of ſweet comfort againſt this Diſcouragement. The ſubſtance of the Chap. ſo much as concerns the Slaying and Reſurrection of the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes take in ſome few Doctrinal Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When Antichriſt is at his height, then does the Work of Reformation begin. There was given me a Reed like unto a Rod, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding me to meaſure the Temple, the Altar, and them that Worſhip therein Verſe 1. A Metaphor taken from Maſons or ſuch Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, who in building a New Houſe, or repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59023:39"/>an Old, do uſe a meaſuring Line. Now is the time come that God will have Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt's Church-ſtate, Worſhip, Ordinances and all to be tried and examined by the Rule of God's Word? 2. When Antichriſtianiſm is at its height, Reformation cannot be without ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. <hi>The Court which is without the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple leave out,</hi> i. e. Let it now be known by the meaſuring Line, that their Temple, Altar, Worſhip, and Worſhippers are none of mine. 3. Antichriſtian Worſhip weighed in the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of the Sanctuary is in God's Account Gentiliſm. <hi>The outer Court is given to the Gentiles,</hi> i. e. To ſuch who though they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſtianity, and that highly too, glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they are the only true Church, yet their Practice pure Gentiliſm, Antichriſtian, Rites and Ceremonies are moſt of them bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from Heathens. 4. Antichriſts tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the holy City, ſhall not be for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, it ſhall be for an appointed time; to wit, 42 Months, Verſe 2. 5. In the height of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtianiſm, Chriſt ſhall have a competent number of ſuch as ſhall give a faithful Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt him. <hi>I will give power unto my two witneſſes, and they ſhall propheſie a thouſand two hundred and threeſcore days cloathed in ſackcloath.</hi> Verſe 3. The Sackcloath notes the meanneſs and lowneſs of their Condition; their number two, their paucity or fewneſs, yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent, out of the Mouth of two or three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſhall every Truth be eſtabliſhed: If this one thouſand two hundred and threeſcore Days be the ſame with the Forty two Months, the time of Antichriſts Reign, as it's very probable, reckoning Thirty Days to every Month, then
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59023:39"/>by the two witneſſes cannot be meant Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy and Miniſtry, becauſe there have not been during the whole time of Antichriſt's Reign, always ſome Magiſtrates, who, as ſuch have given a Teſtimony for Chriſt againſt him; only that Chriſt and in all Ages and Countries a competent number, — as in <hi>England, Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff;</hi> in <hi>Italy, Marſilius Patavinus;</hi> in <hi>Bohemid; John Huſſe</hi> and <hi>Jerom</hi> of <hi>Prague;</hi> in <hi>Saxony<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Luther</hi> and <hi>Melanchton;</hi> in <hi>Helvetia, Zwingli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> in <hi>Baſil, Oecolampadius.</hi> — 6. They that have been called to witneſſing-work, have had a ſpecial Anointing for the Work of their Day. Theſe are the two Olive-Trees and the two Candleſticks ſtanding before the God of the Earth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. In alluſion to the Lamps of the Candleſtick in the Temple, under the Old Teſtament, which were kept burning by two Olive-Trees continually emptying themſelves into them; ſo did Chriſt, out of his Fulneſs continually communicae abundant ſupplies of Grace and Gifts to his Servants. 7. Of all Men in the World Chriſts Martyrs or Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, have the greateſt intereſt in Heaven: If any Man hurteth them, fire proceedeth out of their Mouth, and devoureth their Enemies. An alluſion to what <hi>Elias</hi> did, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.10. They have power to ſhut Heaven, that it Rain not in the Days of their Prophecy. To what <hi>Elias</hi> did, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.1. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.17. They have power over Waters, to turn them into Blood, and to ſmite the Earth with all Plagues as often as they will. This alludes to what <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> did in <hi>Aegypt, verſ.</hi> 5, 6. i. e. They did denounce Wrath, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of ſore judgments that would befall
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59023:40"/>their Perſecutors, and accordingly it came to paſs, God made good their word; they were Wreſtlers, and <hi>Iſraes</hi> indeed, prevailers with God. <hi>Luther</hi> was ſo mighty in Prayer, that <hi>quicquid voluit potuit,</hi> he could do what he would with God.</p>
               <p>From <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. to 11. you have a particular narrative of the ſlaying of the Witneſſes, from thence to 15 of their Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>The time of the ſlaying of the Witneſſes is, 1. Set down when they ſhall have finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Teſtimony, or according to the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, when they are about to finiſh their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, <hi>verſe</hi> 7. i. e. towards the end of the 1260 Days, and towards the end of the Beaſts 42 Months, which is not ſo to be underſtood, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the great miſtake of many, as if they ſhould never after this, witneſs any more, nor Antichriſt Reign any more, but only thus, They ſhall finiſh their Teſtimony in Sackcloath, and their Wilderneſs-State, and he ſhall never Reign again ſo as when he trod under the holy City, while the Church was in the Wilderneſs. 2. The perſon by whom they are ſlain, to wit the Beaſt that aſcendeth out of the bottomleſs Pit, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. i. e. The Pope and thoſe that derive their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from him, as was ſhewn Chap. 9.2, 3. Whether this ſlaying of them be the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their Natural lives only, or a Civil and Spiritual Death, depriving them of all privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges which they enjoyed, both as Men and Chriſtians, in ſilencing Miniſters, not giving them the liberty of their Conſciences, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, according to the word, or ſomething that comprehends both: I ſhall not curiouſly enquire, nor poſitively determine, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59023:40"/>the latter I moſt incline to, for many were ſlain in their Bodies, and others ſuffered a Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Death, by Baniſhments, Excomunications, and otherwiſe. 2. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ace where, is in the Street of the great City, which Spiritually is called <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> verſ. 8. <hi>i. e.</hi> In ſome places of the World, which do profeſſedly own themſelves to be of the Popes Dominions whoſe City is a ſecond <hi>Sodom,</hi> for fulneſs of Bread, Idleneſs, and all manner of Uncleanneſs, and never did Old <hi>Aegypt</hi> abound in heatheniſh Idolatries, and oppreſs the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God more than it. I like will enough of that conjecture that ſpeaks of <hi>Germany,</hi> for it may be fitly called the Street of the great City, as being a principal part of the Roman Empire. The firſt thing that follows upon their being ſlain, is the great Inhumanity of Adverſaries, <hi>they would not ſuffer their Dead Bodies to be put in Graves, for three Days and a half, verſ.</hi> 9. For ſome ſhort time they do pour forth all manner of oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious contempt upon them: The literal ſenſe is not altogether to be rejected; the Papiſts would not ſuffer <hi>Zwinglius's</hi> Body to be Buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: So they ſerved the Admiral of <hi>France,</hi> with many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> others in the <hi>Pariſian</hi> Maſſacre, and in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Days, <hi>Bucer</hi>'s Bones were raiſed, and burnt. 2. <hi>They that dwell upon the Earth ſhall rejoyce over them, and make merry,</hi> becauſe they are rid of their Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menters, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. This muſt be at ſuch a time when the Popiſh party are inſufferably proud, inſulting over the ſlain Servants of God, that had tormented them with a plain Teſtimony againſt all their Abominations. <hi>Mali cum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriam
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59023:41"/>facere non ſinuntur, injuriam ſe acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere exiſtimant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From this Narrative of the ſlaying of the Witneſſes, learn theſe few Inſtructions, 1. Providence ſometimes ſo orders it that God's Servants ſhall well near have finiſhed their Work, before their Enemies can hurt them, that ſo their Teſtimony for Chriſt, may Live when they are dead and gone. 2. Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation has been always attended with great Perſecution. 3. A begun-work of Reformation may have ſuch a ſentence of Death paſs upon it for a ſeaſon, that to all probability it ſhall never have a revival. 4. Chriſt's Witneſſes muſt expect nothing but Barbarity from Men of Popiſh Principles and Spirits. 5. It's no new thing to ſee wicked Men triumphantly inſult over God's perſecuted People. The 1. thing in the Narrative of the Reſurrection of the Witneſſes is the time thereof, <hi>after three Days and a half,</hi> verſ. 11. <hi>Some ſhort time,</hi> ſome apply this to <hi>John Huſſe</hi> and <hi>Jerom,</hi> who were condemned by the Council of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> that began, <hi>Anno</hi> 1414, <hi>December</hi> the 8th. and ended 1418. <hi>May</hi> 22. Three Years and a half. 2. The means by which this was brought about, the Spirit of Life from God entred into them; they were ſtirred up by a Spirit of Zeal from God, to be lively and active in carrying on the work again. 3. Their poſture, <hi>they ſtood upon their feet,</hi> verſ. 11. Either the former ſlain Witneſſes, I mean Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy an Spiritually ſlain, or others of the ſame Principles, and Spirit, did openly appear in and for it again. 4. The effect, great fear fell upon all that ſaw them. 5. <hi>The heard
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59023:41"/>a voice from Heaven, ſaying, Come up hither, and accordingly they did aſcend up to Heaven in a Cloud and their Enemies beheld them,</hi> verſ. 12. The work of Reformation, and Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, became now more glorious than ever before. 6. <hi>About the ſame time there was a great Earthquake and a tenth part of the City fell,</hi> verſ. 13. i. e. When ever the Reſurrection of the Witneſſes is, the Lord ſhall wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully go forth in ſome remarkable Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences and Tremendous Judgments againſt the Roman Empire, to the great weakening there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Some apply it to the <hi>Bohemian</hi> War, after the ſufferings of <hi>Huſſe</hi> and <hi>Jerom,</hi> where <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmundus</hi> had great ſucceſſes againſt the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Army. From all this learn theſe few inſtructions. 1. Commonly the ſufferings of Reformers are ſhort. 2. God's Spirit is the great Engine for carrying on God's Work. 3. Boldneſs in witneſs-bearing, is from God's Spirit, ſtanding on their Feet, an open and a vowed Profeſſion is from the Spirit of Life, from God. 4. Commonly wicked Men begin to be afraid, when they perceive that Perſecution does but make God's People more bold, and God's Work to proſper the more. 5. Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and Separation from Antichriſtian Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions has a great brightneſs of illuſtrious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Glory upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Is this Prophecy of the Slaying and Reſurrection of the Witneſs yet fulfilled? And whereabouts are we of this Age, under the Sixth or Seventh Trumpet? Are the one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand two hundred and threeſcore Days and forty two Month at an end or not?</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:59023:42"/>
               <p>For <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let me premiſe a few things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I come to the thing it ſelf. 1. This cannot be reſolved, unleſs we are at ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty where to fix the beginning of the one thouſand two hundred and threeſcore Days, or the Churches wilderneſs-State, and of the forty two Months, or Antichriſt's firſt Riſe, whether from <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> immediately after the third Century, or from <hi>Boniface</hi>'s time, <hi>Anno</hi> 606. I ſhall endeavour by and by to prove that both did commence from the time that did immediately follow after the firſt 300 Years. 2. It is more than probable, that the one thouſand two hundred and threeſcore Days, and forty two Months are not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood literally, for juſt ſo many Natural Days and Aſtronomical Months, becauſe matter of fact proves that Antichriſt's Reign, and the Churches wilderneſs-State, has been already of a longer continuance, but figuratively and Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally for Days of Years and Months of Years, according to, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4.6. Being an uſual thing for Prophets thus to expreſs themſelves. Theſe things premiſed, I anſwer in the affirmative, That this prophecy has had its accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment already, and the one thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and threeſcore Days and forty two Months are expired; and that for theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If theſe Days and Months did commence from the time, immediately after the firſt three hundred Years, not from ſix hundred ſix, then this Prophecy is fulfilled, and the time paſt, but this is ſo — as may appear, 1. from <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.5, 6. <hi>As ſoon as the Woman brought forth a Man Child, which was caught up to God, ſhe fled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Wilderneſs.</hi> i. e. Immediately after the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59023:42"/>Church was delivered from Heatheniſh Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, her wilderneſs-Eſtate, (the ſame with the one thouſand two hundred and threeſcore Days in this 11th. Chap.) does begin. This is alſo hinted again to us from <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.13, 14. <hi>The Church is nouriſhed in the Wilderneſs, for a time, times and half a time,</hi> i. e. Three Years and a half; the ſame with one thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and threeſcore Days and forty two Months. 2. from 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.7, 8. <hi>The myſtery of iniquity doth already work, only he who now letteth, will let, untill he be taken out of the way, and then ſhall that wicked one be revealed</hi> — i. e. As ſoon as ever the Heathen perſecuting Emperors were removed, and not till then ſhould it appear, what deſign the Devil had, to advance the Myſtery of Iniquity. 3. Though it's true, the Church did not ſuffer from the great Antichriſt, till ſix hundred and ſix; yet all that went before him, after <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> were petty Antichriſts, only at firſt it was but young Days with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt; in ſix hundred and ſix, he was of riper Years, the Churches ſuffering were all that while of the ſame kind, <hi>Majus &amp; minus non variant ſpeciem,</hi> all that went before did but make way for him; and his predeceſſors Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are all of them charged upon him, becauſe he did practically approve of them. And this is the firſt thing that proves the foreſaid Days and Months to be expired, and this Prophecy to be already fulfilled. 2. The inconſequences and abſurdities that follow upon contrary opinions, which do aſſert that it's now a fulfilling, or the futurition of it, as a thing yet to come, make me to conclude that it is paſt. From what has been already ſaid in opening the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59023:43"/>Chap. it's clear, That it is not now a fulfilling. 1. This time cannot be exactly towards the end of the one thouſand two hundred and threeſcore Days and forty two Months, and if it be, When did they begin? 2. Antichriſt is not now at the higheſt, nor the Church at the loweſt. 3. We cannot be ſaid to be the Street of the great City, nor our times times of Popery. 4. We are not the firſt that laid the meaſuring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line to Antichriſt's Temples, Altar and Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. 5. This ſavours of Spiritual Pride, and can hardly be aſſerted, without reflecting upon the glorious Martyrs that have gone before us, as if they had not deſerved the Names of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in reſpect of us, whereas indeed neither we, nor our ſufferings, are worthy once to be named in way of compariſon with them, and their ſufferings: Some do fondly fancy, that nothing is to be witneſſed to, but ſome one Notion of their own. 6. This would argue ingratitude and murmuring, as if we were ſtill in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, when indeed we have rather cauſe to bleſs God, ſaying, We bleſs thee, Lord God Almighty, becauſe thou haſt taken to thee thy great Power, and haſt reigned — The abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that follow upon aſſerting that this is yet to come, and that the foreſaid Days and Months did begin with ſix hundred and ſix, are theſe, 1. By adding one thouſand two hundred and threeſcore to ſix hundred and ſix, will be one thouſand eight hundred and ſixty ſix, about two hundred Years hence. 2. This may breed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity in this preſent Age. 3. For two hundred Years Antichriſt muſt ſtill be a increaſing to a greater height than ever. 4. Either all the glorious late Tranſactions throughout the World,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59023:43"/>have had no tendency to the propheſied ruin of Antichriſt, or if they had, all that has been done, muſt be undone again, and all the Nations that have caſt off the Popes ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, muſt Apoſtatize, and become worſe than before: Is it probable, that God has brought ſo many out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to bring them back again? No verily. 5. If it be determined of God, that Antichriſt's forty two Months ſhall not expire, nor his propheſied Reign begin till then, then it will be but in vain to attempt any thing againſt him all this while.</p>
               <p>And this is the ſecond ground proving the preterition of this Prophecy. There is but one more, to wit the harmony and concurrence of providential Events: Which this prophecy, underſtanding it according to the interpretation given, makes me conclude it is over; add 1260 to 300, and the number that reſults thence is 1560. Now let us inquire a little what ſtate the Church was towards the concluding period of this time, or near thereupon. <hi>Anno</hi> 1546, in the War between the Emperor and Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> the Proteſtants were almoſt total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly routed, the Prince himſelf impriſoned; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates diveſted of their Robes; many Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters baniſhed and impriſoned for not taking the <hi>Interm;</hi> the Antichriſtian party inſult ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly in ſending great Guns and Priſoners, which they had taken as Trophies of an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Victory over <hi>Lutheraniſm:</hi> About the ſame time there was a great perſecution in <hi>France,</hi> in the <hi>Netherlands</hi> under the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> of the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> in <hi>Provence, Anno</hi> 1545. They of <hi>Piedmont</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Savoy:</hi> It is not unknown what was here in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59023:44"/>days. It is obſerved by ſome that within a few of theſe Years, the number of them that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for Chriſt, were 900000, and this may relate to the ſlaying of the Witneſſes; and as for the Reſurrection about 1559, the Work of Reformation had a great reviving in <hi>German.</hi> At a Diet of the Empire at <hi>Ausburg,</hi> by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Authority, the Proteſtants had free li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to make Profeſſion of their Religion, without prejudice to their Eſtates, and civil Privileges; about the ſame time Reformation had a reviving in <hi>Scotland.</hi> In <hi>France</hi> under Charles the 9th, <hi>Anno</hi> 1560. Queen <hi>Mary</hi> Reigned about 1554, and died ſome five Years after, and Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> brought glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous days to Proteſtantiſm in general, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>Marian</hi> days. Beſides all theſe Arguments, my own obſervation of the Acts of Providence at this day, do more and more confirm me in this perſwaſion, however if any can ſhew me more convincing Reaſons to the contary, I hope through Grace I ſhall not be found pertinacious.</p>
               <p>I cannot ſlightly paſs over ſo material a point as this is without drawing ſome practical Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences from it by way of Application.</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. For Inſtruction. 1. The longeſt Day that ever was had an end: Antichriſt's forty two Months have their period. 2. When Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors are at the higheſt, then their Downfal draws nigh; <hi>Nihil violentum durabile.</hi> 3. O that all the Sons of Wickedneſs would be wiſe, and inſtructed from what has befallen others, to tremble and fear God becauſe of his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. 4. Chriſt's Witneſſes do carry on his Work by their Sufferings, as well as Services,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59023:44"/>Paſſive Obedience is as acceptable to God, and uſeful to others, as Active. 5. No Cauſe of Chriſt, ſealed with a bloody Teſtimony, ſhall ever be quite loſt. 6. The Reformed Churches that have in any meaſure caſt off the Yoak of Antichriſtianiſm, are highly to be eſteem'd of; tho' it was never intended of God that Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation ſhold ſtand at what it did begin, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Doctrine, Worſhip or Diſcipline; yet the ſtate of the Primitive Reformers was a Heaven upon Earth in compariſon of what their Prececeſſors ſtate was.</p>
               <p>More particularly from theſe things we may venture to make ſome ſober conjecture concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Diſpenſation this Age is under.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If this Prophecy of the Witneſſes be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled about an hundred Years ago, then we are now under the 7th Trumpet, which contempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizeth with their Reſurrection, or does at leaſt follow immediately upon it. 2. The Work of Reformation is not to begin; the Right-hand of the moſt High has already laid the Foundation. 3. Antichriſt has been already at the higheſt, and is now a going down the Wind; all the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of Men and Devils ſhall not be able to raiſe him again to what once he was, nor to ſupport or keep him from falling; tho' this and two or three Nations more ſhould Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize to Popery more than ever, yet it's nothing contrary to my aſſertion, unleſs <hi>Bohemia, Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerland, Helvetia, Hungary, Holland,</hi> and all in <hi>Germany, France, Sweden,</hi> and other parts, do profeſſedly return to <hi>Rome</hi> again, and become more Idolatrous than before, which ſhall never be. 4. We ſhall never know ſuch another ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Witneſſes as this. 1. Thoſe were in the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59023:45"/>Wilderneſs, the ſuffering Witneſſes of after A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſhall be out of the Wilderneſs. 2. They were then in Sackcloth, after Ages ſhall never know ſuch a mournful Condition. 3. They ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered before the Temple of God was opened in Heaven, which is under the 7th Trumpet, <hi>ch.</hi> 11. there was not before them any conſiderable vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Separation from the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> not ſo with us. 4. There were but two then, <hi>i. e.</hi> a few in compariſon of what ſhall be after, if we ſuffer for Chriſt now, we ſhall have many Co-partners. 5. That very work of God which has been begun amongſt us, I mean Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Doctrine, Worſhip and Diſcipline, ſhall ſome where or other in God's own time and way, go on and proſper, maugre all oppoſition.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, The conſideration and belief of this Truth, that the Witneſſes are ſlain and riſen, may teach us how to demean our ſelves in this Day, 1. Towards God. 2. Enemies. 3. One another. 4. In reſpect of our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Towards God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We are Monſters for Ingratitude, if we do not trumpet forth his Praiſes aloud, for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us forth in ſuch a glorious Age and Time; certainly if our Godly Anceſtors had ſeen and heard what we now do, eſpecially they that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved about an hundred Years ago, would have ſaid, Now the Kingdom of our God and of his Chriſt is Come. 2. Be very Patient under all the Corrections and Chaſtiſements of this Good God. 1. Your Sufferings are but a Flea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite to the Sufferings of others that have gone before you. 2. Your Puniſhments are ſtill leſs than your Sin's deſerts. 3. Conſider what the Glorious Son of God hath ſuffered for you,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59023:45"/>and yours is nothing. 4. It's a moſt glorious, honourable and advantageous thing to ſuffer for Chriſt in a righteous Cauſe; See 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.13, 14, 15, 16. with ſeveral others formerly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to you. 5. Your ſufferings may be ſharp for a Seaſon, but ſhort. 6. Your Sufferings af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a begun Work of Reformation, are for the Trial of your Faith and Patience, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.6, 7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.36, 37, 38. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.12. Here is the Patience of the Saints; here are they that keep the Commandments of God, and the Faith of Jeſus. 7. The iſſue of your Sufferings will be Glorious to your ſelves, but dreadful to your Enemies, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6.</p>
               <p>Towards Enemies.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Look upon them as the Rod of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you for your ſins of Ingratitude, Earthly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindedneſs, Carnality, Pride, Self-ſeeking Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy, Formality, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. If your Enemies are any kin to Antichriſt, you need not, you ought not to fear them, with a ſlaviſh fear, for they are falling and going down, even when they ſeem to riſe. 3. Seeing you can in ſome meaſure gueſs at the iſſue and event of things, pity and pray for Perſecutors, as knowing what that Wrath that abides them, is, unleſs, they repent. 4. Abhor the very thoughts of a ſinful compliance with any Antichriſtian pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions and abominations in God's Worſhip, if you had lived a hundred Years ago, there had been ſome colourable excuſe for your Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and Compliance, but now there can be one, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. <hi>ult. My little Children keep your ſelves from Idols.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:59023:46"/>
               <p>Towards one another.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Love and Honor all under what Name or Notion ſoever that have but their Faces <hi>Zion</hi> ward, eſpecially ſuch as have Suffer'd, do now, or may yet Suffer for the Word of God and for the Teſtimony of Jeſus; the rebukes of God upon Profeſſors, call aloud to them to lay aſide their ſinful differences and diviſions which have undone them, and to love one another not in Word but in Deed, with a pure heart fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently: You have all common Enemies, and why you ſhould not love one another I know not. 2. If any that bear the Name of Chriſt ſhould ſolicit you to joyn with them in any ſinful irregular courſe to work your Deliverance, heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en not to them; God himſelf does now ſtand engaged to go on with that which is God's Work indeed, and therefore he needs not your hand nor help.</p>
               <p>In reſpect of your ſelves.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Tho' the great ſlaying of the Witneſſes be paſt, yet each of us ought to be always pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the greateſt of Tryals, becauſe no particular Perſon can at any time promiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf an abſolute exemption from Sufferings from this time forth to the end of the World; and it ſtands with reaſon in ſhould be ſo, for the Deſtruction of Antichriſt being gradual, by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſeveral Vials; when one Vial has done its work, there is ſtill ſomething more of him to be deſtroyed, and his utter Deſtruction will not be till the end of the World, how can it then be otherwiſe but ſo long as he has any power or being he will he making ſome buſtle againſt thoſe that oppoſe; Some are of opinion that even after the converſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:59023:46"/>which will be a moſt glorious time, the Church will have great troubles and that for forty five Years together, <hi>Daniel</hi> 12. Begin. Nay, and after the 1000 Years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.1. They ſhall be in as great trouble as ever they knew from the beginning of the World to that Day, which will be immediately before the coming of the Son of God to Judgment. Many have ſtrongly fancied, that the time was come that the ſhould have nothing to do but to rule the World; the Lord in mercy convince them of their miſtakes; certainly a glorious Day may be look'd for before this World be at an end; but it is ſo called comparatively, <hi>i.e.</hi> in reſpect of our preſent Day and Times that ar paſt. 2. This calls aloud upon us to be deeply humbled before the Lord, becauſe of our manifold ſins and unſuitableneſs of Spirit to the Work of our Day: We may well ſay thus, Is the Work of Reformation now upon the Wheel of Providence? And is Antichriſt a declining? Ah, how does the Work ſtick and go on ſo ſlowly? Sure it's my Sins and others that retards and hinders it. When I conſider the great Diſtempers of the Spirits of all ſorts of Profeſſors, I do not at all wonder at what has befallen us. 3. Let us therefore, by all means, labour for ſuch a Spirit as may ſuit with the Work of our Day; a Spirit of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to know what is God's Work, and what ours; to know what is Antichriſtian, and what not—a Spirit of Wiſdom to find out ſuch Holy and righteous ways as may moſt conduce for the carrying on of this Work; a Spirit of Humility, Mortification, Self-denial, Sincerity, Faithfulneſs, holy Courage and Boldneſs, a
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59023:47"/>Spirit of Prayer, Faith and Zeal, for God's Glory.</p>
               <p>They that would yet know more particularly under what diſpenſation we now are, and what hereafter may be expected, muſt ſtudy well the 7th Trumpet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. End, and the ſeven Vials, Chap. 16. I will but juſt give a very ſhort hint at each of the Vials, and ſo ſhut up all. The 1ſt is poured out upon that which is the Earth in the Antichriſtian World, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals of the Popiſh Kingdom are ſtruck at, and ſuch Doctrines upon which the whole ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Antichriſtianiſm is built, without which it cannot ſtand, no more than the Fabrick of this Univerſe without the Earth. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſays of <hi>Luther,</hi> that he committed two unpardonable faults, in medling with the Popes Mitre and the Monks Bellies. Antichriſt's Ruine is the Churches Riſe; the confuting of their Antichriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines did clear up the principal Fundamental Truths of the Goſpel. 2. Upon the Sea, <hi>i. e.</hi> Their Worſhip and Ordinances by which they trade on with another. The firſt Reformers were ſo taken up with the clearing up of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal part of the Goſpel, that they could not have the while to think of mattes of Worſhip, which was done to ſome purpoſe after in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> by <hi>Chemnitius</hi> and others. 3. Is upon the Rivers and Fountains of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>i. e.</hi> The Romiſh Clergy: It's by them the Chriſtians of the Antichriſtian World are moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtended; they come from the Sea, and run into it; they were Originally bred by the Romiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and are the great ſupporters of it; they are Wells of Water, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. And <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.5, 6, 7. It's they that have ſhed the Blood of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59023:47"/>Saints and Prophets. According to this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation theſe three Vials are at leaſt in ſome meaſure poured forth already, only more may be yet expected. 4. Upon the Sun, <hi>i. e.</hi> Either ſome that are eminent for upholding Antichriſt in his civil power and juriſdiction, ſuch as the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> the Pope's Eldeſt Son, or the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> or ſomething that's a great light to them in reſpect of their Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal State, ſuch as is the whole Body of their Cannon Law — or both theſe. 5. Is upon the ſeat of the Beaſt; this may be underſtood of the Deſtruction of <hi>Rome</hi> or the Pope's Principality; as the 5th Trumpet ſet him upon his Throne, the 5th Vial ſhall Dethrone him. 6. Dries up the great River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> i. e. Deſtroys the Great <hi>Turk</hi> and his Empire, which ſhall make way for the Kings of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> to go up into their own Land, <hi>i. e.</hi> The ſhall the <hi>Jews</hi> be Converted, the Glory of which time I have diſcourſed at large in my Treatiſe of the Fifth Monarchy. 7. and laſt puts an end to all. Antichriſt is not only utterly ruined, but alſo <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> all ſorts of Chriſts, and the Churches Enemies. The Lambs Marriage Day is ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized before God, Angels and Men, and his Spouſe is caught up to himſelf to be with the Lord for ever: The Spirit and the Bride ſaith, Come, even ſo come quickly, Lord Jeſus, <hi>Amen.</hi> And let every Soul ſay, <hi>Amen. Truly God is good to Iſrael, and to ſuch as are of a clean heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Gloria perpetuo ſit tribuenda Deo.</closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
